<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>
                    <!-- Title --> [a machine-readable transcription]</title>
                <author><!-- Author --></author>
                <author><!-- Author 2 --></author>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName><!-- Encoder's name --></persName>
                    <resp>Creation of machine-readable version.</resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno xml:id="2013-01-15"><!-- ID of this e-file  e.g., 2013-01-15 --></idno>
                <authority>SARIT: Search and Retrieval of Indic Texts</authority>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>Copyright Notice</p>
                    <p>
                        <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/" type="licence"
                            >Distributed by <ref target="http://sarit.indology.info" type="url"
                                >SARIT</ref> under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0
                            Unported License. </ref>
                    </p>
                    <p>Under this licence, you are free <list>
                            <item>to Share — to copy, distribute and transmit the work</item>
                            <item>to Remix — to adapt the work </item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Under the following conditions:</p>
                    <p>
                        <list>
                            <item>Attribution — You must attribute the work in the manner specified
                                by the author or licensor (but not in any way that suggests that
                                they endorse you or your use of the work).</item>
                            <item>Share Alike — If you alter, transform, or build upon this work,
                                you may distribute the resulting work only under the same or similar
                                license to this one.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>More information and fuller details of this license are given on the Creative
                        Commons website.</p>
                    <p>SARIT assumes no responsibility for unauthorised use that infringes the
                        rights of any copyright owners, known or unknown.</p>
                </availability>
                <date>2013</date>
            </publicationStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note>This gets printed by Philologic with the main bibliographical entry</note>
        </notesStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title><!--  --></title>
                    <editor><!--  --></editor>
                    <publisher><!--  --></publisher>
                    <pubPlace><!--  --></pubPlace>
                    <date><!--  --></date>
                    <note><!--  --></note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>

            <!--  Pick and choose bits of the following, as appropriate -->

            <editorialDecl>
                <p>The published edition from which this e-text was transcribed is printed in the
                    Devanāgarī script. The electronic text below is in a lossless transliteration
                    using the Latin alphabet. The transliteration scheme used is the IAST (<ref
                        target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Alphabet_of_Sanskrit_Transliteration"
                        >The International Alphabet of Sanskrit Transliteration</ref>). IAST differs
                    in small ways from ISO 15919, but is preferred by most working Sanskrit
                    scholars. Conversion of this file to ISO 15919 can be achieved by performing the
                    following replacements throughout the file: <code> ṛ -> r̥ and ṃ -> ṁ </code>
                </p>
                <p>Text divison is as Devanāgarī ("ityevam" not "ity evam".) </p>
                <normalization>
                    <p>Initial vowel elision for avagraha is reversed and marked with a + sign:
                        e.g., "prathamo+adhyāyaḥ"</p>
                </normalization>
                <p>Similarly, external sandhis are undone and marked: "yathā+amarā"</p>
                <p>The ampersand (&amp;) was used by the inputters as an anchor to mark places in
                    the e-text where the printed edition has a footnote, and again with the text of
                    the related footnote being placed nearby in the e-text. I have regularized these
                    footnotes in many, but not all, cases, changing them to <tag>note</tag>s. The
                    use of the ampersand may still be irregular in places, and needs to be checked
                    against the edition, and some notes have been omitted and need to be added from
                    the edition.</p>
                <p>The notes by Trivikramātmaja Ācārya are included in the e-text . using the
                        <tag>note</tag> element. </p>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>A first cut has been made at distinguishing verse and prose. Prose passages
                        are enclosed in the normal <tag>p</tag> tags. Verse passages are grouped
                        within the line-group tag, <tag>lg</tag>, and individually tagged as verse
                        lines, <tag>l</tag>.</p>
                    <p>Inserted comments <tag>!-- subdivision --</tag> and <tag>!-- /subdivision
                            --</tag> around passages where the text section is subdivided into a
                        level below that of the surrounding text. These comment tags need to be
                        replaced with something better, but we can't use <tag>div3</tag>, for
                        example, because of the problem of TEI's policy on tessellation. See TEI
                        Guidelines P5, section 4.3.2, et passim. Nor are these subdivisions floating
                        text, or groups, or other obvious units. They could be marked with
                            <tag>span</tag>s (<tag>span type="interesting" spanTo="#xy"</tag>
                            ...<tag>anchor xml:id="xy"</tag>) or <tag>milestone</tag>s, but these
                        mechanisms seem clumsy. The question stands for now. </p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2011-07-07" who="???">
                <list>
                    <item>Added TEI encoding.</item>
                    <item><!--  other changes -->
                    </item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>

    </teiHeader>


    <text xml:lang="sa-Deva"> <!-- or sa-Latn -->
        <body>

            <p>
                <!-- The encoded e-text itself -->
            </p>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
