<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>SARIT Encoding Guidelines</title>
	<title type="sub">Full Version</title>
        <author>Liudmila Olalde, Andrew Ollett, Patrick McAllister</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>"Project SARIT: Enriching Digital Text Collections in Indology" (Bilalteral Digital Humanities Programme DFG/NEH), 2013-2017.</publisher>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Copyright Notice:</p>
          <p>Copyright 2017 SARIT</p>
          <licence>
            <p>Distributed under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International licence.</ref> Under this licence, you are free to:</p>
            <list>
              <item>Share — copy and redistribute the material in any medium or format.</item>
              <item>Adapt — remix, transform, and build upon the material for any purpose, even commercially.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The licensor cannot revoke these freedoms as long as you follow the license terms.</p>
            <p>Under the following terms:</p>
            <list>
              <item>Attribution — You must give appropriate credit, provide a link to the license, and indicate if changes were made. You may do so in any reasonable manner, but not in any way that suggests the licensor endorses you or your use.</item>
              <item>ShareAlike — If you remix, transform, or build upon the material, you must distribute your contributions under the same license as the original.</item>
            </list>
            <p>More information and fuller details of this license are given on the Creative Commons website.</p>
          </licence>
          <p>SARIT assumes no responsibility for unauthorised use that infringes the rights of any copyright owners, known or unknown.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>TEI version produced by pandoc and manual editing based on <ref target="https://github.com/sarit/sarit-pm/blob/91f6ea5d78c2385e10a7c3a85ac36968df853abe/docs/encoding-guidelines-full.html">sarit-pm/91f6ea5d78c2385e10a7c3a85ac36968df853abe/docs/encoding-guidelines-full.html</ref>.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="../../saritcorpus.xml#patmcall" when="2017-06"><p>This document is based on <ref target="https://github.com/sarit/sarit-pm/blob/91f6ea5d78c2385e10a7c3a85ac36968df853abe/docs/encoding-guidelines-full.html">sarit-pm/91f6ea5d78c2385e10a7c3a85ac36968df853abe/docs/encoding-guidelines-full.html</ref>.</p></change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
	<head>Introduction</head>
      <p>This is a <hi rendition="simple:italic">preliminary</hi> set of
guidelines for using TEI to encode textual variation for Indic texts.
The TEI recommendations on textual criticism are
<ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/TC.html">here</ref>.
In addition, there is a
<ref target="http://marjorie.burghart.online.fr/?q=en/content/tei-critical-apparatus-cheatsheet">cheatsheet</ref>
for TEI critical apparatuses written by Marjorie Burghart. If you are
new to TEI encoding, we recommend that you take a few minutes to read
<ref target="http://tei.oucs.ox.ac.uk/GettingStarted/html/in.html">Getting
Started with TEI</ref>, and then Marjorie Burghart's cheatsheet for a
quick familiarization with encoding textual variation in particular. The
motivation for this document is that the general TEI guidelines are not
specific enough to guarantee consistent encoding within a project, and
other sets of guidelines are too specialized.</p>
<p>The immediate goal of this document is to inventory the basic types
of text-critical markup that will be included in
<ref target="http://sarit.indology.info">SARIT</ref> texts. SARIT is a
project that collects TEI versions of Sanskrit and Prakrit texts,
promotes standards for their encoding, and develops applications for
their use. At present, most texts included in SARIT have very minimal
text-critical markup, or none at all. But we would like to include
text-critical markup in future phases of the project and add related
functionality to the website.</p>
<p>This document will therefore allow us</p>
<list>
  <item>
    <p>to render this markup correctly and consistently in any
    SARIT-related applications;</p>
  </item>
  <item>
    <p>to design applications that produce and interact with this kind
    of markup on behalf of the end-user, and especially an
    <hi rendition="simple:bold">online editor</hi> for TEI-based texts;
    and</p>
  </item>
  <item>
    <p>to document and promote standards for text-critical markup in the
    field of Indology.</p>
  </item>
</list>
<p>Encoding an existing critical edition in TEI and producing a new
critical edition from scratch are very different tasks.
<hi rendition="simple:bold">This document is primarily concerned with
encoding editions that already exist in print.</hi> This means,
<hi rendition="simple:italic">inter alia</hi>, that we produce digital
facsimiles of print editions, which may differ radically from the
editions that we <hi rendition="simple:italic">would</hi> produce if we
were starting from scratch. Although these texts may be improved
subsequently - indeed such digital editions are intended as a
<hi rendition="simple:italic">starting point</hi> for future editorial
work - we want to ensure that the digital edition presents
<hi rendition="simple:italic">all</hi> of the information that is
presented in the printed edition.</p>
<p>This document provides guidelines for an
<hi rendition="simple:italic">analytic</hi> apparatus, in which the
information of the textual apparatus is highly structured, using the
text-critical module of the TEI guidelines. This is not the only way to
encode textual variation. In many editions, text-critical information is
presented in unstructured footnotes or endnotes. There are benefits to
such unstructured apparatus entries: people can easily read them and
understand them. However, there are also benefits to using a structured
and analytic apparatus. For example, the analytic approach permits the
reconstitution of entire witnesses, and also allows the readings of
particular witnesses (or editors) to be aggregated and systematically
compared.</p>
<p>The <hi rendition="simple:bold">language</hi> and
<hi rendition="simple:bold">script</hi> depends on the project, but we
insist in these guidelines that texts can be converted from one script
to another. Thus, even if you are preparing a TEI edition in Roman
transliteration, you should prepare it in such a way that it can easily
be converted into Indic scripts such as Devanāgarī. Be particularly
careful of “orphaning” combining signs such as vowel-marks
(<hi rendition="simple:italic">mātrā</hi>s) and anusvāra:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<rdg>ṃ</rdg>
</egXML> might look fine in transliteration, but in
Devanāgarī it will appear as <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<rdg>ं</rdg>
</egXML>. Such conversions
are never perfect because of the different word-separation conventions
for Indic scripts.</p>
<p>Please <hi rendition="simple:bold">contribute</hi> ideas and
suggestions based on your experience, and please identify yourself in
any contributions to this document. Thank you!</p>

<div>
  <head>The apparatus entry in overview</head>
  <p>Text-critical markup will generally take the form of entries in a
critical apparatus. Most of the traditional means of representing
textual variation, such as the “critical apparatus” itself at the bottom
of a printed page, relate to variation at the level of the letter, word,
and phrase. Higher-level variation (such as the addition, omission or
rearrangement of whole chapters or sections) is usually discussed in
text-critical notes, which may be printed with or in the critical
apparatus. Typically, variation at the level of the letter, word and
phrase will be encoded in a structured apparatus entry (<gi>app</gi> with
one or more <gi>rdg</gi> elements), and variation at or above the level
of a structural unit (a verse or prose paragraph) will be signalled in a
<ref target="text-crit-note">text-critical note</ref> (<gi>app</gi> with
a <gi>note</gi> element).</p>
<p>An apparatus entry consists of two obligatory parts: the
<hi rendition="simple:italic">reading</hi>, and the
<hi rendition="simple:italic">authority</hi> on which the reading is
based. In this context, the <hi rendition="simple:italic">lemma</hi> is
another word for the <hi rendition="simple:italic">reading</hi> of the
base text, which may or may not be repeated explicitly in the apparatus
entry, depending on the encoding strategy used.</p>
<p>The <hi rendition="simple:italic">reading</hi>, as noted above,
should generally be no longer than a few words.
<hi rendition="simple:bold">The reading must not be shorter than a
syllable.</hi> The reason for this restriction is that we want to avoid
TEI elements that begin with combining letters in Indic scripts ( े, ो,
ा, ृ, etc.). In cases where the variation is “really” at the level of
the diacritical mark, or <hi rendition="simple:italic">mātrā</hi>, we
recommend encoding the rest of the syllable anyway (e.g., when there is
variation between ke and ko, encode
<hi rendition="simple:italic">ke</hi> or
<hi rendition="simple:italic">ko</hi> and not
<hi rendition="simple:italic">k</hi>+<hi rendition="simple:italic">e</hi>
or <hi rendition="simple:italic">o</hi>).</p>
</div>
<div>
  <head>The authority</head>
  <p>One of the two main parts of the apparatus entry is the
<hi rendition="simple:italic">authority</hi> on which the reading is
based. If we confine ourselves to digital transcriptions of printed
editions, the authority might be one of the following:</p>
<list type="unordered">
  <item>
    <p>a <hi rendition="simple:italic">manuscript</hi> (in the cast of
    most <ref target="reading1">variant readings</ref> );</p>
  </item>
  <item>
    <p>a modern <hi rendition="simple:italic">edition</hi> of the work,
    or some other piece of modern scholarship (in the case of
    emendations);</p>
  </item>
  <item>
    <p>a <hi rendition="simple:italic">parallel text</hi> (e.g., a
    quotation of the text in another work, in the case of
    <ref target="restorations">restorations</ref>);</p>
  </item>
  <item>
    <p>the editor or reviewer of the digital text himself/herself (in
    the case of <ref target="corrections">corrections</ref>).</p>
  </item>
</list>
<p>Generally we refer to manuscript readings in the apparatus by a
<hi rendition="simple:italic">siglum</hi> that uniquely identifies the
manuscript (e.g., “म”). For modern editions, the most common practice is
to also use a <hi rendition="simple:italic">siglum</hi> (e.g., “KM”).
For books and articles, one common practice is to use the scholar's name
in the apparatus (e.g., “Kangle”). For
<ref target="restorations">parallel texts</ref> (including testimonia),
apparatus entries may refer to simply the author of the parallel text
(e.g., “Hemacandra”), its title (e.g., “Kāvyānuśāsana” or “KA”), or they
might employ a more specific citation (“KA p. 200 l. 5”). Some editions
include a separate apparatus for parallel texts.</p>
<p>We want all of the references in the critical apparatus to be clear
and unambiguous, and we want to make it easy for readers to look up the
full bibliographic entry that the reference corresponds to. For this
reason, <hi rendition="simple:bold">all authorities referenced in the
apparatus must be defined elsewhere in the document</hi>, or
alternatively <hi rendition="simple:bold">in an external authority
file</hi>. At the moment, we suggest referring to these authorities by
<hi rendition="simple:italic">xml:id</hi>. That is, if you want to
report the readings of a manuscript “K,” then your apparatus entry must
refer to an XML element identified by the ID “K”, as follows:</p>
<p>In the <hi rendition="simple:italic">text</hi>:</p>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
  
  <app><lem
	   source="#ed">mai</lem><rdg
	   wit="#K">nai</rdg></app>vaṃ

</egXML>
<p>In the <hi rendition="simple:italic">header</hi> :</p>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
  
  <listWit>
    <witness xml:id="K">Manuscript
    K</witness>
  </listWit>

</egXML>

<p>In this system, every reference to an “authority” in the apparatus
should be interpreted as a reference to an element that defines the
authority and tells readers where and how it might be consulted. Those
elements will be contained in the source description
(<gi>sourceDesc</gi>); see the appendix,
<ref target="appendix">Describing Witnesses</ref> , for more
information.</p>
<p>Most of the time, a reference to the authority itself - a manuscript,
say, or a printed edition - is sufficient; sometimes, more information,
such as page, folio, or line numbers, will have to be added. In those
cases, the additional information should be supplied within a
<gi>ref</gi> element inside the apparatus entry:</p>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
  
  <app><rdg source="#K"><ref>p.
  100 l. 10</ref>naivaṃ</rdg></app>

</egXML>
<p>This entry refers to a “source” <hi rendition="simple:italic">K</hi>,
which is a printed edition of a text rather than a manuscript, and to
the precise location in <hi rendition="simple:italic">K</hi> where the
quoted reading is found. See
<ref target="restorations">restorations</ref> below.</p>
</div>
      </div>
<div>
  <head>The text and the apparatus</head>
<p>Printed texts almost always have an
<hi rendition="simple:italic">external</hi> apparatus, which is printed
either at the bottom of the page or in an appendix. SARIT recommends the
use of an <hi rendition="simple:italic">internal</hi> apparatus, in
which the apparatus entries are embedded directly into the text. Adding
TEI encoding to a text will therefore mean converting an external
apparatus to an internal apparatus.</p>
<p>The TEI P5 guidelines distinguish three strategies for
<ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/TC.html#TCAPLK">linking</ref>
the critical apparatus to the text:</p>
<list type="unordered">
  <item>
    <p>the <hi rendition="simple:italic">location-referenced</hi>
    method, in which the apparatus entry is embedded in the text at a
    certain point;</p>
  </item>
  <item>
    <p>the <hi rendition="simple:italic">double-end-point-attached</hi>
    method, which embeds the apparatus entry in the text at a certain
    point <hi rendition="simple:italic">but also</hi> refers to another
    point of reference where the “lemma” of the apparatus begins or
    ends.</p>
  </item>
  <item>
    <p>the <hi rendition="simple:italic">parallel-segmentation</hi>
    method, where the “lemma” is placed inside the apparatus entry.</p>
  </item>
</list>
<p>Because we will generally be converting footnotes into apparatus
entries, the <hi rendition="simple:italic">location-referenced</hi>
method will generally be most appropriate. For some projects, the
parallel-segmentation method might be desirable and feasible, because it
encodes all of the relevant information into the apparatus entry itself.
However, it is often difficult to determine the lemma to which a reading
given in the apparatus of a printed texts corresponds (and impossible to
isolate the lemma programmatically); moreover, the
<hi rendition="simple:italic">location-referenced</hi> and
<hi rendition="simple:italic">double-end-point attached</hi> method
allow for the possibility of conflicting apparatus entries, and the
<hi rendition="simple:italic">parallel-segmentation</hi> method
generally does not. Examples will be given in the following cases.</p>
</div>
<div>
  <head>Reporting a manuscript reading</head>
  <p>This is perhaps the most common situation. The apparatus (or a
text-critical footnote) refers to the reading of another witness. In
such a case, the text might read:</p>
<p>न2 तदेकमुखप्रेक्षितामतिवर्तते ।</p>
<p>And the apparatus or footnote reads:</p>
<p>2. म.भ. नटभेदमुखप्रेक्षकमति ।</p>
<p>The apparatus entry is embedded in the text, and refers to the
witnesses by their xml:id, which will have been assigned already in the
source description (see <ref target="manuscripts">below</ref> ):</p>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
  
  <p>न<app><rdg wit="#म
  #भ">नटभेदमुखप्रेक्षकमति ।</rdg></app>
  तदेकमुखप्रेक्षितामतिवर्तते ।</p>

</egXML>

<p>This example uses the
<hi rendition="simple:italic">location-referenced</hi> method. The
<hi rendition="simple:italic">parallel-segmentation</hi> method would
be:</p>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
  
  <app>
    <lem source="#ed">न तदेकमुखप्रेक्षितामतिवर्तते
    ।</lem>
    <rdg wit="#म #भ">नटभेदमुखप्रेक्षकमति
  ।</rdg></app>

</egXML>

<p>Since projects often need to convert hundreds or thousands of
apparatus entries, this method is generally not feasible, since it
requires a human editor to determine the beginning and ending of the
apparatus entry.</p>
<p>In both cases, we are using an <gi>app</gi> element to contain the
entire apparatus entry, and each distinct reading within the apparatus
entry is given by the <gi>rdg</gi> element. The
<hi rendition="simple:italic">witness</hi> of the reading is referred to
in the value of the <att>wit</att> attribute, if it is a manuscript; if the
reading is based on a printed text, that text is referred to in the
value of the <att>source</att> attribute. The <gi>lem</gi> element is required in
the parallel-segmentation method, but optional in the
location-referenced method; its primary purpose in the
location-referenced method is to supply information (such as witnesses
or responsibility) about the reading of the base text.</p>
<p>Here is another example. The text and apparatus read:</p>
<p>अवराहेहि1</p>
<p>1. B अवराहो वि.</p>
<p>The encoding would be (again using the location-referenced
method):</p>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
  
  अवराहेहि<app><rdg wit="#B">अवराहो
  वि</rdg></app>

</egXML>
<p>Now suppose we have two different readings. The text and apparatus
read:</p>
<p>7चैव तत्त्वतः</p>
<p>7. अ. चापि । क्ष.म. चाभिधत्स्व नः</p>
<p>Here we have to use the location-referenced method, because the scope
of the given readings is different:</p>

<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
  
  <app>
    <rdg wit="#अ">चापि</rdg>
    <rdg wit="#क्ष #म">चाभिधत्स्व नः</rdg>
    </app>चैव तत्त्वतः

</egXML>

<p>Note in this case that the different witnesses to the same reading,
क्ष and म, are referred to in the same <att>wit</att> attribute of the same
<gi>rdg</gi> element, since they have an identical reading.</p>

<div>
  <head>Different readings of the same witness</head>
  <p>If two scholars read the same witness (say, a manuscript)
differently, we may use the <att>source</att> attribute on the <gi>rdg</gi> element
<hi rendition="simple:italic">together with</hi> the <att>wit</att> element. The
value of <att>source</att>, although typically the name of the scholar in
apparatus entries, should point to the bibliographic citation in which
the scholar presented the reading (usually an edition).</p>
</div>
<div>
  <head>Reporting the reading of another edition</head>
  <p>This is exactly parallel to the case of reporting the reading of a
manuscript. The only difference is that we refer to a printed text
rather than to a manuscript. And to refer to printed texts, we use the
attribute <att>source</att> rather than <att>wit</att>. Hence for a text and apparatus that
read:</p>
<p>विज्जुप्फुरियं2</p>
<p>2. Laber विज्जुप्फुरिओ.</p>
<p>We write:</p>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
  
  विज्जुप्फुरियं<app><rdg source="#Laber">विज्जुप्फुरिओ</rdg></app>

</egXML>

</div>
</div>
<div>
  <head>Reporting omissions</head>
  <p>Suppose we have in the text and apparatus:</p>
<p>रामादौ4</p>
<p>4. म.भ. अयं भागो नास्ति ।</p>
<p>In this case, we have the option of either reproducing the exact
wording of the editor of the printed text by placing it in a
text-critical note, as discussed
<ref target="text-crit-note">below</ref>, or “translating” his short
comment in Sanskrit into TEI. We generally recommend the latter
strategy, when the comment is unambiguous. Here, the editor is clearly
referring to an omission, and we encode omissions with an
<hi rendition="simple:italic">empty</hi> <gi>rdg</gi> element:</p>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
  
  रामादौ<app><rdg wit="#म
  #भ"/></app>

</egXML>

<p>Note that when we use the location-referenced method, an empty
<gi>lem</gi> element is not interpreted in the same way as an empty
<gi>rdg</gi> element. The latter means that the witness referred to lacks
the reading of the base text; the former simply gives us additional
information about the reading of the base text (its witnesses, sources,
etc.). If we want to represent the fact that one or more witnesses
include material that is not found in the base text, we do not present
it as an “omission” in the base text but as an “interpolation” in the
witnesses (see below).</p>
</div>
<div>
  <head>Reporting lacunae</head>
  <p>Lacunae are not omissions, but places in which the manuscript (or its
exemplar) has been damaged. Encoding lacunae using the
location-referenced method of apparatus attachment is difficult. If the
exact locations of the lacunae are known, the beginnings and ends can be
marked with a <gi>lacunaStart</gi> and <gi>lacunaEnd</gi> element, which
must be contained within a <gi>lem</gi> or <gi>rdg</gi> element. Further
details might be provided in a <gi>note</gi> element contained within the
<gi>lem</gi> or <gi>rdg</gi> element. Here is one example that uses the
<att>type</att> attribute to show that the given readings represent lacunae:</p>
<p>[तव]8 लोलं मनः</p>
<p>8 A: ••• (lacuna marked by 3 points); B: (lacuna marked by a blank of
two spaces); C: ••••• (lacuna marked by 5 points): तव supplied from
D.</p>
<p>According to the location-referenced method:</p>

<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
  
  तव<app>
  <lem wit="#D">तव</lem>
  <rdg wit="#A"
       type="lacuna">•••</rdg>
  <rdg wit="#B" type="lacuna">
  </rdg>
  <rdg wit="#C"
       type="lacuna">•••••</rdg>
  </app> लोलं मनः

</egXML>

<p>According to the parallel-segmentation method:</p>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
  
  <app>
    <lem wit="#D">तव</lem>
    <rdg wit="#A"
	 type="lacuna">•••</rdg>
    <rdg wit="#B" type="lacuna">
    </rdg>
    <rdg wit="#C"
	 type="lacuna">•••••</rdg>
    </app>लोलं मनः

</egXML>
</div>
<div>
  <head>Reporting interpolations</head>
  <p>An interpolation, in this context, is a reading that is found in one
or more manuscript witnesses but has been excluded from the base text
because the editors have judged it to be not original.</p>
<p>Examples - the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Raghupañjikā</hi>
edition?</p>
</div>

<div>
  <head>Emendations by modern scholars</head>
<p>Emendations are traditionally referred to the
<hi rendition="simple:italic">name</hi> of the scholar who proposed the
reading. However, it is generally more helpful to readers to refer to a
specific bibliographic item (a book or article) in which the scholar has
proposed the reading. Thus we refer to emendations with the <att>source</att>
attribute, and we make the value of this attribute point towards a
bibliographic citation (in cases where a bibliographic citation is not
available, we must refer to a <gi>name</gi> entity somewhere in the
header). Note that we use <att>source</att> rather than <att>wit</att>, because the scholars
are not relying on any particular “witnesses” (the case of restorations
from parallel texts is different and will be discussed
<ref target="restorations">below</ref> ). Hence the following text and
apparatus entry</p>
<p>स चोभयोर3पि</p>
<p>3. उभयोऽपि - De</p>
<p>would be encoded as follows:</p>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
  
  स चोभयोर<app><rdg
  source="#De">उभयोऽपि</rdg></app>पि

</egXML>
<p>Another example:</p>
<p>वासनात्मनेह1</p>
<p>1. ते - De</p>
<p>would be encoded as follows:</p>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
  
  वासनात्मनेह<app><rdg
  source="#De">ते</rdg></app>

</egXML>
<p>This example shows how the readings reported in the editions often do
not make sense without further information, and hence require us to use
the <hi rendition="simple:italic">location-referenced</hi> method rather
than the <hi rendition="simple:italic">parallel-segmentation</hi>
method.</p>
<p>Another example includes some additional information about the lemma
as well as a reading ascribed to “RK,” or Ramakrishna Kavi. We are not
told whether this is Kavi's <hi rendition="simple:italic">reading</hi>
of the manuscript, or his <hi rendition="simple:italic">emendation</hi>
, but he will appear in the <att>source</att> attribute in any case. We are also
not told where Ramakrishna Kavi proposed this reading, and thus what
bibliographic citation #RK should point to, but this questions need to
be settled on a project-by-project basis.</p>
<p>स्थायी भवत्य2नुपचितः</p>
<p>2. H.Ms.; भवत्यनुपचितः RK.</p>
<p>The encoding would be:</p>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
  स्थायी भवत्य<app><lem
  wit="#HMs"/><rdg
  source="#RK">भवत्यनुपचितः</rdg></app>नुपचितः

</egXML>


<p>In this case, the attribution of the
<hi rendition="simple:italic">lemma</hi> to the Hoshiarpur manuscript is
given through the empty element <gi>lem</gi> with the attribute
<att>wit</att> set to <val>#HMs</val>. This simply provides information about the
reading of the base text. We do not, however, know exactly where the
reading of the Hoshiarpur manuscript begins and ends.</p>
<p>Sometimes the exact nature of the scholar's responsibility is not
clear from the editor's note or the apparatus entry. We should generally
try to translate these into TEI-compliant forms. Hence in the following
example, where the reading of the base text is “supported” by De but no
alternative readings are given, we make De a “source” for the lemma:</p>
<p>कालात्तु8</p>
<p>8. supported by De.</p>
<p>as follows:</p>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
  कालात्तु<app><lem
  source="#De"/></app>
</egXML>

<p>One more example involves manuscript readings and emendations
reported both in the text and in the apparatus:</p>
<p>चक्कस(ना)8मवहू का(क)9न्तसहाइणिआ ।</p>
<p>8. Kavi - सना(णा) 9. क-not read by Kavi;</p>
<p>This is an unfortunately typical example. We are given to know in an
earlier note that corrections to the text, as well as the footnotes, are
the responsibility of V.M. Kulkarni, the editor (of the second edition
of this part of the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Nāṭyaśāstra</hi> ). We
must figure out that the readings that Kulkarni regards as correct are
those <hi rendition="simple:italic">in</hi> the parenthesis, and the
incorrect readings of the manuscript(s) are outside of the parentheses;
we must also be aware that parentheses are also used for
<hi rendition="simple:italic">Kulkarni's</hi> additions to the text
(readings not found in M. Ramakrishna Kavi's earlier edition), as well
as <hi rendition="simple:italic">Kavi's</hi> additions to the text. The
apparatus entry might look like this, assuming we simply want to encode,
and not correct, Kulkarni's text:</p>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
  चक्कसना<app>
  <lem resp="#VMK">ना</lem>
  <rdg wit="#MRK">णा</rdg>
  <rdg wit="#mss"/>
  </app>मवहू क<app>
  <lem resp="#VMK">क</lem>
  <rdg wit="#MRK"/>
  <rdg wit="#mss">का</rdg>
  </app>न्तसहाइणिआ

</egXML>


<p>The first apparatus entry shows that Kavi added णा after स and
Kulkarni changed it to ना (incorrectly); the second shows that Kavi
failed to read the का of the manuscript(s), which Kulkarni has emended
to क. None of the manuscripts are actually referred to in the apparatus
entry, so we have to use the dummy-referent #mss. In the
parallel-segmentation method this line would read:</p>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
  चक्कस<app>
  <lem resp="#VMK">ना</lem>
  <rdg wit="#MRK">णा</rdg>
  <rdg wit="#mss"/>
  </app>मवहू <app>
  <lem resp="#VMK">क</lem>
  <rdg wit="#MRK"/>
  <rdg wit="#mss">का</rdg>
  </app>न्तसहाइणिआ
</egXML>
</div>
<div>
  <head>Corrections by the editor or reviewer</head>
<p>The editor or reviewer will sometimes want to communicate that the
witness <hi rendition="simple:italic">reads</hi> X, where X is clearly a
mistake or corruption for Y. In such cases, the editor's reading is not
an <hi rendition="simple:italic">emendation</hi> (especially when the
editor does not accept the corrected reading as original), but simply a
<hi rendition="simple:italic">correction</hi>. For such cases we use the
<gi>choice</gi> element, which has two children: <gi>sic</gi> reporting
the reading as given, and <gi>corr</gi> reporting the corrected reading.
<gi>corr</gi> should have a resp (responsibility) attribute that
identifies the person who made the correction. Here is an example where
the correction occurs in a reading that the editor does not accept:</p>
<p>सुयणा वि दुज्जणा इह विणिम्मिया भुयणे1</p>
<p>1. <hi rendition="simple:bold">B</hi> सुयणा वि णिम्मिआ दुज्जणाइ इह
सुवणे [ = दुज्जणा इह भुवणे ]</p>
<p>This would be encoded as:</p>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
  <app>
    <lem>सुयणा वि दुज्जणा इह विणिम्मिया भुयणे</lem>
    <rdg wit="#B">सुयणा वि णिम्मिआ
    <choice>
      <sic>दुज्जणाइ इह सुवणे</sic>
      <corr resp="#ed">दुज्जणा इह
      भुवणे</corr>
    </choice>
    </rdg>
  </app>
</egXML>
</div>
<div>
  <head>Restorations from parallel passages</head>
  <p>The term “parallel texts” includes anything that is not in the direct
manuscript tradition of the text under consideration. Parallel texts
might be:</p>
<list type="unordered">
  <item>
    <p>quotations of the text in a later text, either anonymously or
    attributed (e.g., a verse from Dharmakīrti's
    <hi rendition="simple:italic">Pramāṇavārttika</hi> in
    Śālikanāthamiśra's
    <hi rendition="simple:italic">Prakaraṇapañcikā</hi> );</p>
  </item>
  <item>
    <p>anthologizations of the text (e.g., a verse from Rājaśekhara's
    <hi rendition="simple:italic">Bālarāmāyaṇa</hi> in the
    <hi rendition="simple:italic">Saduktikarṇāmṛta</hi> )</p>
  </item>
  <item>
    <p>reworkings or adaptations of the text (e.g., Hemacandra's
    adaptation of Abhinavagupta's discussion of
    <hi rendition="simple:italic">rasa</hi> in his
    <hi rendition="simple:italic">Kāvyānuśāsana</hi> ).</p>
  </item>
</list>
<p>In these cases, the reading is referred to another text, and
preferably with a pointer to a location in that text (either a page
number or a canonical reference such as chapter and verse). The parallel
text thus serves as a <hi rendition="simple:italic">source</hi> , and
should be referred to in the <att>source</att> attribute. (In some cases, the
parallel text is read from a manuscript, in which case the <att>wit</att>
attribute should be used.) <hi rendition="simple:italic">References</hi>
to locations within the parallel text should be encoded using a
<gi>ref</gi> element inside of the reading element.</p>
<p>Hence the apparatus entry:</p>
<p>गता6</p>
<p>6. याता for गता KA., p. 89.</p>
<p>should be encoded as follows:</p>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
  गता<app><rdg
  source="#KA"><ref>p.
  89</ref>याता</rdg></app>

</egXML>

<p>In this case, there is also the possibility of using the
parallel-segmentation method:</p>

<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
  <app>
    <lem source="#ed">गता</lem>
    <rdg source="#KA"><ref>p.
    89</ref>याता</rdg>
  </app>
</egXML>
<p>Here is another example, where the parallel text was a source of the
reading of the base text (lemma):</p>
<p>7स्फीतदशायां</p>
<p>7. KLV.</p>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
  <app><lem
  source="#KLV"/></app>स्फीतदशायां

</egXML>
<p></p>
<p>The person who is <hi rendition="simple:italic">responsible</hi> for
identifying the parallel might also be referred to in the <att>resp</att>
attribute. Thus, if we want to say that V. M. Kulkarni (VMK) found a
parallel passage in the Kāvyakalpalatāviveka (KLV), we might make #VMK
point to the bibliographic entry for Kulkarni's article, and #KLV to the
bibliographic entry for the edition of the KLV, and encode as
follows:</p>
<egXML  xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
  
  <app>
    <lem source="#KLV"
	 resp="#VMK">भावो</lem>
  </app>

</egXML>
<p>Sometimes a parallel text is adduced in favor of a reading, although
the parallel text itself is not a “witness” to the reading. Here is one
example:</p>
<p>अनुकार्येऽनुकर्तर्यपि चानु5सन्धानबलात् - इति ।</p>
<p>5. विचारा - De; but रामादिरूपता Hemacandro,KA,p. 89</p>
<p>In this case, Hemacandra's
<hi rendition="simple:italic">Kāvyānuśāsana</hi> has a passage that
corroborates the reading अनुसन्धान॰ rather than De's विचारा॰ (although
it is difficult to see this, and indeed difficult to see exactly what
De's reading corresponds to in the edition). This information should be
put into a <gi>note</gi> element that qualifies the reading proposed by
De. When we convert this entry to TEI, and correct some of the
typographic mistakes, we get:</p>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
  अनुकार्येऽनुकर्तर्यपि चानु<app>
  <rdg resp="#De">विचारा<note
  xml:lang="en">but <ref target="#KA"/>
  p. 89 has <foreign
  xml:lang="sa-Deva">रामादिरूपता</foreign></note></rdg>
  </app>सन्धानबलात् - इति ।
</egXML>
</div>
<div>
  <head>Readings noted in a commentary</head>
<p>An editor might refer to the reading of a commentary - either the
reading that the commentator <hi rendition="simple:italic">accepts</hi>
, or a reading that he <hi rendition="simple:italic">mentions</hi> . [No
examples of an apparatus entry that features such readings.]</p>
</div>
<div>
  <head>Recording types of variation</head>
  <p>It will often make sense to
<hi rendition="simple:italic">classify</hi> the readings (whether they
are manuscript readings, conjectures, emendations, etc.) based on the
kind of variation that they index. For example, there may be a group of
variants that are orthographic in nature: one group of manuscripts
consistently reads अ where another group consistently reads य. Depending
on the needs of the project, this variation can be “typed” as
orthographic with an attribute of the <gi>app</gi> element.</p>
<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">[SARIT will probably need a constrained
list of apparatus “types” if this attribute is to be of any
use.]</hi></p>
</div>
<div>
  <head>References to other texts</head>
    <p>Some editions provide references in the body of the text, for example
in parenthesis, and other editions provide references in footnotes that
are found together with variant readings at the bottom of the page.
Since these references are not strictly speaking apparatus entries, we
do not use the TEI element <gi>app</gi> for them. Instead, we encode them
as notes, with the <gi>note</gi> element. Further recommendations are
beyond the scope of this document.</p>
</div>

<div xml:id="text-crit-note">
  <head>The text-critical note</head>
<p>Text-critical notes such as are found in the critical apparatus of a
printed text should also be encoded as apparatus entries. A <gi>note</gi>
element within an <gi>app</gi> element will be interpreted as such a
text-critical note.</p>
<p>The language of the apparatus may be
<hi rendition="simple:italic">the same as</hi> or
<hi rendition="simple:italic">different from</hi> the language of the
encoded text. In the latter case, it is necessary to specify in the TEI
Header that all text-critical notes (app/note) should have a certain
<att>xml:lang</att> attribute: en for English, sa-Deva for Sanskrit in the
Devanāgarī script, etc. (See the
<ref target="http://sarit.indology.info/exist/apps/sarit/docs/encoding-guidelines.html">SARIT
Guidelines</ref> for a discussion of language attributes.) Sometimes,
for example when a text has been edited several times, there might be
text-critical notes in two languages; in such cases, one will be the
“default” language defined in the TEI Header, and the other must be
noted with an <att>xml:lang</att> attribute on each <gi>note</gi> element. Take
care, however, to enclose any Sanskrit text or readings in the
<gi>note</gi> element within an element with the appropriate <att>xml:lang</att>
attribute. (The default TEI element for foreign text is
<gi>foreign</gi>).</p>
<p>The <gi>note</gi> element may can contain any of the elements allowed
in the TEI P5 DTD. Typically, notes found in the apparatus will not have
paragraph-level formatting, so they should contain text rather than
elements such as <gi>p</gi>. Here is an example:</p>
<p>1 सदाचारं प्रमाणयता ...</p>
<p>1 The following verse is found in the beginning of the
<hi rendition="simple:italic">Avaloka</hi> only in the Adyar Telugu
Manuscript:</p>
<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">vācakaḥ praṇavo yasya krīḍāvastv
akhilaṃ jagat |</hi></p>
<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">śrutir ājñā, vapur jñānaṃ, taṃ vande
devakīsutam ||</hi></p>
<p>F. Hall noted in his Preface (p. 5, fn.) to his edition of the
<hi rendition="simple:italic">Daśarūpaka</hi> that in one of the
manuscripts of the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Avaloka</hi> the
following verse, which is different from the one now seen, was
found:</p>
<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">praṇipatya śivaṃ sāmbam ācāryaṃ
bharataṃ tathā |</hi></p>
<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">kriyate daśarūpasya vyākhyānaṃ
dhanikena vai ||</hi></p>
<p>This was however rejected by F. Hall as spurious.</p>
<p>I would encode this note as follows (the <att>xml:lang</att> attribute of the
<gi>note</gi> element may be omitted if it is specified elsewhere):</p>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
  <app>
    <note xml:lang="en">The following verse is found
    in the beginning of the <hi
    rend="italics">Avaloka</hi> only in the Adyar
    Telugu Manuscript:
    <quote>
      <lg xml:lang="sa-Latn">
	<l>vācakaḥ praṇavo yasya krīḍāvastv akhilaṃ jagat
	|</l>
	<l>śrutir ājñā, vapur jñānaṃ, taṃ vande devakīsutam
	||</l>
      </lg>
    </quote>
    F. Hall noted in his Preface (p. 5, fn.) to his edition of the
    <hi rend="italics">Daśarūpaka</hi> that in one
    of the manuscripts of the <hi
    rend="italics">Avaloka</hi> the following verse,
    which is different from the one now seen, was found:
    <quote>
      <lg xml:lang="sa-Latn">
	<l>praṇipatya śivaṃ sāmbam ācāryaṃ bharataṃ tathā
	|</l>
	<l>kriyate daśarūpasya vyākhyānaṃ dhanikena vai
	||</l>
      </lg>
    </quote>
    This was however rejected by F. Hall as
    spurious.</note>
    </app>सदाचारं प्रमाणयता ...
</egXML>
</div>
<div xml:id="appendix">
  <head>Appendix: Describing Witnesses</head>
<p>By “witnesses” we mean any source that attests to a given reading
supplied in the apparatus. Thus “witnesses” includes
<hi rendition="simple:italic">manuscripts</hi> as well as printed
editions, scholarly books and articles, and so on. All of these
witnesses should be described in the <hi rendition="simple:bold">source
description</hi> (<gi>sourceDesc</gi>) in the TEI Header, but manuscript
sources and printed sources will generally be described differently.
Each witness must be assigned a unique <att>xml:id</att> by which it is referred
in the apparatus entries.</p>

<div xml:id="manuscripts">
  <head>Manuscripts</head>

  <p>Manuscripts may be defined and referred to in a number of ways
according to the TEI guidelines. We recommend the use of the
<gi>listWit</gi> element within the source description, for several
reasons: this can include <gi>witness</gi> elements that refer to
manuscripts as well as groups of manuscripts, whereas the alternatives
(e.g., defining manuscripts in <gi>listBibl</gi> with <gi>msDesc</gi>) do
not allow for the possibility of defining a group of manuscripts. The
children of the <gi>listWit</gi> element might be manuscripts (defined
either through <gi>msDesc</gi> or <gi>witness</gi>) or groups of
manuscripts (defined through <gi>witness</gi>). In any case, the <att>xml:id</att>
of the manuscript(s) should serve as the siglum by which the witness is
referred to in the apparatus. Here is an example:</p>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
  <listWit>
    <witness xml:id="HMs">Hoshiarpur
    manuscript.</witness>
    <witness xml:id="म">Kavi's manuscript
    "म."</witness>
    <witness xml:id="भ">Kavi's manuscript
    "भ."</witness>
    <witness xml:id="mss">All of the
    manuscripts.</witness>
  </listWit>
</egXML>

<p>The TEI guidelines
<ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/TC.html#TCAPWL">recommend</ref>
that manuscripts defined in the list of witnesses be supplied with a
pointer to a complete description of the manuscript elsewhere, either
within the same project (using the <gi>msDesc</gi> element) or in an
external resource.</p>
</div>
<div xml:id="printedsources">
  <head>Printed sources</head>
<p>Printed sources should be defined in a <gi>listBibl</gi> element in
the source description. For the content and structure of the
<gi>listBibl</gi> element, please consult the TEI P5 Guidelines
<ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/CO.html#COBITY">on
this topic</ref>. Additionally, we recommend the <att>type</att> attribute of
<gi>bibl</gi> or <gi>biblStruct</gi>, with the values of article, book,
incollection, phdthesis, etc., so the TEI bibliography entry can easily
be converted into other formats. Here are a few examples:</p>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
  <listBibl>
    <bibl xml:id="VMK"
	  type="incollection">
      <author>
	<name><surname>Kulkarni</surname>
	<forename>V. M.</forename></name>
      </author>
      <title level="a">Abhinavabhāratī Text: Professor
      Kangle's Emendations</title>
      <biblScope unit="pp" from="113"
		 to="123">113-123</biblScope>
      <title level="m">Vidyopaasanaa: Studies in Honour
      of Harivallabh C. Bhayani</title>
      <editor>
	<name>
	  <surname>Mistry</surname>
	  <forename>P. J.</forename>
	</name>
      </editor>
      <editor>
	<name>
	  <surname>Modi</surname>
	  <forename>Bharati</forename>
	</name>
      </editor>
      <pubPlace>Mumbai</pubPlace>
      <pubPlace>Ahmedabad</pubPlace>
      <publisher>Image Publications</publisher>
      <date when="1999">1999</date>
    </bibl>
    <bibl xml:id="KA" type="book">
      <title level="m">Kāvyānuśāsana [with
      Alaṃkāracūḍāmaṇi
      and Viveka] of Ācārya Hemacandra with Two Anonymous
      Ṭippaṇas</title>
      <editor>
	<name>
	  <surname>Parikh</surname>
	  <forename>Rasiklal</forename>
	</name>
      </editor>
      <editor>
	<name>
	  <surname>Kulkarni</surname>
	  <forename>V. M.</forename>
	</name>
      </editor>
      <pubPlace>Bombay</pubPlace>
      <publisher>Śrī Mahāvīra Jaina
      Vidyālaya</publisher>
      <date when="1964">1964</date>
    </bibl>
  </listBibl>
</egXML>
</div>
</div>
<div xml:id="people">
  <head>People</head>
<p>Normally, the “people” referred to in the critical apparatus are
scholars who have published their readings, corrections, emendations
etc. in a book or article. And thus these “people” are generally treated
as “sources” in the apparatus, and their names should point to a
bibliographic entry as exemplified above.</p>
<p>The “default” place for such information is a list of persons, which
is contained in the <gi>particDesc</gi> (the description of
participants), which is contained in the <gi>profileDesc</gi> (profile
description) of the TEI Header. For instance, a reading which the editor
attributes to S. K. De but which is not presented in any publication
(since it was communicated to the editor personally, for example) should
might refer to #De, which would be defined in the Header as follows:</p>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
  <listPerson>
    <person xml:id="#De">
      <name>
	<surname>De</surname>
	<forename>S. K.</forename>
      </name>
    </person>
  </listPerson>
</egXML>
</div>
<div xml:id="references">
  <head>References</head>
<p><hi rendition="simple:bold">Discussions on TEI-L:</hi></p>
<p><ref target="https://listserv.brown.edu/?A1=ind1505&amp;L=tei-l#7">https://listserv.brown.edu/?A1=ind1505&amp;L=tei-l#7</ref></p>
<p><ref target="https://listserv.brown.edu/archives/cgi-bin/wa?A1=ind1505&amp;L=TEI-L#18">https://listserv.brown.edu/archives/cgi-bin/wa?A1=ind1505&amp;L=TEI-L#18</ref></p>
<p><hi rendition="simple:bold">Chapter 12 of the TEI P5
Guidelines:</hi></p>
<p><ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/TC.html">http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/TC.html</ref></p>
<p><hi rendition="simple:bold">Marjorie Burghart's Cheat Sheet:</hi></p>
<p><ref target="http://marjorie.burghart.online.fr/?q=en/content/tei-critical-apparatus-cheatsheet">http://marjorie.burghart.online.fr/?q=en/content/tei-critical-apparatus-cheatsheet</ref></p>
<p><hi rendition="simple:bold">SARIT Encoding Guidelines:</hi></p>
<p><ref target="http://sarit.indology.info/exist/apps/sarit/docs/encoding-guidelines.html">http://sarit.indology.info/exist/apps/sarit/docs/encoding-guidelines.html</ref></p>
</div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
