<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>SARIT Encoding Guidelines</title>
        <author>Liudmila Olalde, Andrew Ollett, Patrick McAllister</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Produced by pandoc.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="level1">
        <head>Preface</head>
        <p>This document presents guidelines for the creation of digital texts
  in Sanskrit, Prakrit, and other Indian languages.</p>
        <p>These guidelines are maintained by SARIT
  (<ref target="http://sarit.indology.info">http://sarit.indology.info</ref>).
  SARIT maintains a collection of digital texts that conform to the
  standards of the Text Encoding Initiative (TEI) and provides tools for
  browsing and seaching these texts. These guidelines have two main
  purposes:</p>
        <list type="unordered">
          <item>
            <p>to document the standards that the SARIT project has followed
      in the creation of its own digital texts;</p>
          </item>
          <item>
            <p>to provide guidance for how to apply the TEI standards to texts
      in Sanskrit and other Indian languages;</p>
          </item>
          <item>
            <p>to promote the production of TEI-conformant digital texts in
      the community of Indian studies.</p>
          </item>
        </list>
        <p>The guidelines come in two varieties:
	<hi rendition="simple:bold">simple</hi> and
	<hi rendition="simple:bold">full</hi>.</p>
        <list type="unordered">
          <item>
            <p>The <hi rendition="simple:bold">simple</hi> guidelines (this
      document) document the minimal level of encoding that SARIT
      requires of texts in its collections. These guidelines provide a
      straightforward path “from printed edition to digital text,” and
      should suffice for the purposes of most projects.</p>
          </item>
          <item>
            <p>The <hi rendition="simple:bold">full</hi> guidelines supplement
      the simple guidelines. The TEI standards that SARIT follows allow
      for encoding features of a text that aren’t typically included in
      “plain” digital texts. The full guidelines provide guidance for
      these advanced features. If you want your digital text to reflect
      textual variation (in the form of a critical apparatus or
      otherwise), cross-references within the text or references to
      other texts, or any kind of controlled vocabulary (persons, works,
      places, etc.), then the <hi rendition="simple:bold">full</hi>
      guidelines are for you.</p>
          </item>
        </list>
        <p>Texts that are encoded according to the simple guidelines can
  always be “enhanced” at a later stage with the markup described in the
  full guidelines. </p>
      </div>
      <div type="level1">
        <head>Introduction</head>
        <p>Digital texts come in a variety of formats, but the texts
  distributed by SARIT are XML files that conform to standards of the
  Text Encoding Initiative (TEI).</p>
        <p/>
      </div>
      <div type="level1">
        <head>What is XML?</head>
        <p>In the days of publishing before word-processing, copy editors used
  to "mark up" an author's typed or handwritten manuscript for
  the printer, using written abbreviations to indicate structural points
  in the text, like headings, indents or font changes. XML is simply a
  collection of markup conventions for digital documents. Most web pages
  use XML or an XML-like form of markup. HTML is a special case of XML.
  The key feature of XML is its use of
  <hi rendition="simple:bold">elements</hi>, which start and end with
  tags in angle-brackets, and signal some
  <hi rendition="simple:bold">editorial</hi> intention relating to the
  text:
  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
	     <p>This is a paragraph.</p>
  </egXML></p>
  <p>Elements can be nested within each other:</p>
  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
	

!!!<p>This is !!!<hi>highlighted text!!!</hi>.!!!</p>
</egXML>
        <p>Elements can also be given
	<hi rendition="simple:bold">attributes</hi>:</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
	
		 <p>This is <hi rend="bold">an element</hi>.</p>
	</egXML>
        <p>In a <hi rendition="simple:bold">well-formed</hi> XML document,
  every starting tag corresponds to an ending tag, and vice versa, and
  all of the elements are arranged hierarchically and without
  overlapping. But in order to be useful, the document must use elements
  in a well-defined and standardized way. A document that formally
  defines what elements may be used in an XML document, and how they may
  be used, is called a <hi rendition="simple:bold">schema</hi>.</p>
        <p>Once you have well-formed and valid XML, what can you do with it?
  There are many computer programs that can read an XML text and do all
  sorts of interesting things. One of the first things you may want to
  do is to check that the file you have painstakingly prepared really is
  well-formed. That is the work of a so-called "XML Parser."
  It can check your text and flag up inconsistencies in the markup,
  making sure that it validates against a schema. But that is only the
  beginning.</p>
        <p>Since XML provides a structure that computers can easily navigate,
  it is easy to find any part of a document. You can index these parts
  in a database for searching, or you can transform them into a format
  that human beings can read: HTML, RTF, or PDF. XML texts can be
  converted into almost any other format, or processed in many
  complicated ways using a super-strength version of search-and-replace
  called XSLT. </p>
        <div type="level2">
          <head>How do I type XML texts?</head>
          <p>An XML document has no hidden codes, and can be typed with
    <hi rendition="simple:bold">any</hi> writing program from the
    simplest editor to the most feature-rich word processor. Many modern
    programs have XML "modes" that provide things like
    syntax-highlighting or online help; others have been created
    specifically for typing XML. Several of these programs have XML
    Parsers built in to them, so that they can check your input as you
    go along and perhaps even format it nicely on the screen. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="level2">
          <head>What is TEI?</head>
          <p>The Text Encoding Initiative produces guidelines for encoding
    texts as XML documents and schemas for validating those documents.
    The TEI guidelines have been used, and continue to be used, in
    hundreds of text-encoding projects, and form the basis of many other
    subprojects (such as EpiDoc). They are actively maintained and
    well-supported by a growing number of applications, and hence they
    currently represent “The Right Way” to produce digital texts. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="level2">
          <head>Structure, not presentation</head>
          <p>We want to reflect the <hi rendition="simple:bold">structure</hi>
    of text, and not the <hi rendition="simple:bold">presentation</hi>
    of the text on the pages of a printed edition. This means that we
    typically do not encode formatting such as bold face, italics,
    centered text, and so on. Rather, we encode the logical features of
    the text that these formatting decisions represent. Although TEI
    provides a rendering attribute (<att>rend</att>) for
    many elements, we do not recommend using it: if text is rendered in
    a certain way, try to figure out
    <hi rendition="simple:bold">why</hi> it is rendered that way, and
    then encode the structural reasons for that presentational choice.
    Thus, if a text is centered on the page because it represents a
    colophon, use <gi>trailer</gi> rather than
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><p rend="center"/></egXML>. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="level2">
          <head>Getting started</head>
          <p>All SARIT documents start the same way. The file begins with an
    <hi rendition="simple:bold">XML declaration</hi>, a processing
    instruction that tells whatever program opens the document that it
    is written in XML. This XML declaration is always the same:</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <![CDATA[
               <?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
      ]]>
    </egXML>
          <p>All valid XML files must have one, and only one,
    <hi rendition="simple:bold">top-level element</hi>. Since SARIT
    documents are TEI documents, this top-level element is going to be
    <gi>TEI</gi>. This means that the second line of the file, after the
    XML declaration, will look something like the following:
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <![CDATA[
               <TEI xml:id="sarit__XML-ID_HERE" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"/>
      ]]>
	</egXML></p>
          <p>This element has two attributes. The
    <att>xml:id</att> is a unique identifier for the
    document. Your choice for this unique identifier will depend on your
    project. The <att>xmlns</att> attribute tells whatever
    program opens the document that the names of the XML elements are
    the names defined by the Text Encoding Initiative: for example, that
    the element <gi>p</gi> is what the TEI defines
    as <gi>p</gi>, and not what any other
    authority defines as <gi>p</gi>.</p>
          <p>The last line of the document will close the
    <gi>TEI</gi> element, and hence it will always
    be <tag><![CDATA[</TEI>]]></tag>. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="level2">
          <head>Further details</head>
          <p/>
          <div type="level3">
            <head>Comments</head>
            <p>The XML processor will ignore anything that is contained
      between <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><![CDATA[<!--]]></egXML> and <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><![CDATA[-->]]></egXML>. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="level3">
            <head>The xml:id and xml:lang attributes</head>
            <p>The <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">xml:id</egXML> attribute assigns a unique
      identifier to an element, so that the element can be referenced
      from anywhere else in the document, or even in a corpus of
      documents. But the functions that depend on unique
      identifiers—indexing and cataloguing, for example—are better left
      to automatic processes. And since ~xml:id@s need to be unique, and
      need to have a certain format (NCName), it’s easy for humans to
      introduce errors that will throw a wrench into these automatic
      processes. That’s why SARIT recommends
      <hi rendition="simple:bold">against</hi> the use of @xml:id~
      attributes within a document. If @xml:id@s are needed for
      technical reasons, it’s better to let those technical reasons
      determine how these @xml:id@s are to be generated and assigned. A
      document will still be valid if you use @xml:id@s, and there are
      certain cases (such as referencing readings in a critical
      apparatus to the main text) where you might find @xml:id@s useful.
      But in general, nothing is lost by omitting @xml:id@s, and often
      compatability with certain programs (such as SARIT’s XML database)
      is gained by omitting them.</p>
            <p>The <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">xml:lang</egXML> attribute, on the other
      hand, should be used systematically and carefully when preparing a
      SARIT document. This attribute tells us what language is
      represented by the text of the element to which it is attached.
      SARIT follows the two-letter language codes defined by <ref target="http://loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/">http://loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/</ref>,
      and in most cases these language codes are followed by a code for
      the script, as follows:</p>
            <list type="unordered">
              <item>
                <p><egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">en</egXML>: English (in the Latin script by
          default);</p>
              </item>
              <item>
                <p><egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">sa-Latn</egXML>: Sanskrit in the Latin
          script (Roman transliteration);</p>
              </item>
              <item>
                <p><egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">sa-Deva</egXML>: Sanskrit in the Devanāgarī
          script.</p>
              </item>
              <item>
                <p><egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">pra-Latn</egXML>: Prakrit in the Latin
          script (Roman transliteration);</p>
              </item>
              <item>
                <p><egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">pra-Deva</egXML>: Prakrit in the Devanāgarī
          script.</p>
              </item>
            </list>
            <p>See SARIT’s <hi rendition="simple:bold">character-encoding
      guidelines</hi> regarding issues of script and
      transliteration.</p>
            <p>The <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">xml:lang</egXML> attribute is
      <hi rendition="simple:bold">heritable</hi>: if you say that a
      certain element is in a certain language, then all of the children
      of that element are assumed to be in the language as well. Thus we
      need to specify a language at the highest level of its occurrence:
      <gi>teiHeader</gi> will almost always take
      the attribute
      <att>xml:lang</att> with value <val>en</val>, and <gi>text</gi>
      will almost always take the attribute
      <att>xml:lang</att> with value <val>sa-Deva</val> or <val>sa-Latn</val>
      (see above). Apart from this initial specification, we only need
      to specify the language of an element if it is different from the
      language of its parent element: for example, if you have an
      English note to a Sanskrit text, you will generally give the
      <gi>note</gi> element the
      <att>xml:lang</att> attribute the value <val>en</val>.</p>
          </div>
          <div type="level3">
            <head>Dealing with whitespace</head>
            <p>Because XML uses tags rather than whitespace elements
      (line-breaks and indentation) to mark the logical structure of the
      document, XML has no hard-and-fast rules for whitespace: a single
      element, consisting of a starting-tag, content, and an ending-tag,
      might occur on one, three, or forty lines. Different text editors
      also have different conventions for putting whitespace into XML
      documents.</p>
            <p>XML processors usually trim the whitespace at the beginning and
      end of an element. (See <ref target="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/XML_Whitespace#Trimming">http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/XML_Whitespace#Trimming</ref>.)
      Usually this will not change the actual text that you wish to
      encode. Whitespace requires attention, however, when within an
      element text and XML elements occur side-by-side, that is, when
      using inline XML elements (elements which have text before or
      after them). In cases like this, it’s important to put meaningful
      spaces <hi rendition="simple:bold">outside</hi> of the inline tags
      rather than inside the tags, thus:</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
	
!!!<element>XYZ !!!<element>ABC!!!</element> XYZ!!!</element>
</egXML>
            <p>Rather than:</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
	

!!!<element>XYZ!!!<element> ABC !!!</element>XYZ!!!</element>

</egXML>
            <p>which will lose the spaces when it is processed.</p>
            <p/>
          </div>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="level1">
        <head>The TEI Header</head>
        <p>One of the advantages of using TEI is the ability to include all
  kinds of structured metadata. When we create a SARIT document, we are
  not just transcribing the text, but also providing the following:</p>
        <list type="unordered">
          <item>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:bold">cataloguing</hi> information, for
      example the title and author of the text;</p>
          </item>
          <item>
            <p>information about the document’s
      <hi rendition="simple:bold">source</hi>, such as the edition that
      the</p>
          </item>
        </list>
        <p>digital text is based upon;</p>
        <list type="unordered">
          <item>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:bold">legal</hi> information, such as the
      license and authority under which the text</p>
          </item>
        </list>
        <p>is made available;</p>
        <list type="unordered">
          <item>
            <p>information about the <hi rendition="simple:bold">encoding</hi>
      of the document; and</p>
          </item>
          <item>
            <p>information about the
      <hi rendition="simple:bold">revisions</hi> that have been made to
      the document over</p>
          </item>
        </list>
        <p>the course of its history.</p>
        <p>All of this information is provided in a section of the document
  called the <hi rendition="simple:bold">header</hi>, which is contained
  in the element <gi>teiHeader</gi>.
  <gi>teiHeader</gi> is a direct child of the
  top-level element <gi>TEI</gi>. And since the
  metadata will typically be in English, we typically specify the
  language of the <gi>teiHeader</gi> element with
  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">xml:lang="en"</egXML> TEI Header has three obligatory sections: one for
  the description of the file (<gi>fileDesc</gi>), one for the
  description of the file’s encoding
  (<gi>encodingDesc</gi>), and one to record the
  file’s history (<gi>revisionDesc</gi>). We’ll
  talk about these three sections in order. But SARIT also provides a
  template document that shows how the header should be structured
  (<ref target="https://github.com/sarit/SARIT-corpus/blob/master/00-sarit-tei-header-template.xml">https://github.com/sarit/SARIT-corpus/blob/master/00-sarit-tei-header-template.xml</ref>).</p>
        <p>It is important to distinguish between the
  <hi rendition="simple:bold">work</hi> and a specific
  <hi rendition="simple:bold">representation</hi> of that work. A
  <hi rendition="simple:bold">work</hi> is an abstract object, such as
  <hi rendition="simple:bold">Hamlet</hi> or
  <hi rendition="simple:bold">Abhijñānaśakuntalā</hi> considered as
  ideas in the mind. A printed edition of a work and a digital edition
  of a work are both <hi rendition="simple:bold">representations</hi>.
  In most cases a specific printed edition will be the
  <hi rendition="simple:bold">source</hi> of the digital edition and
  must be acknowledged as such. Since printed editions are protected by
  copyright laws—although not to the same degree in all
  jurisdictions—you must ensure that you are legally entitled to use the
  printed edition as the source of the digital edition. </p>
        <div type="level2">
          <head>The file description</head>
          <p>The file description element
    (<gi>fileDesc</gi>) contains the most
    essential metadata: a statement of the title and author of the text,
    which is essential for cataloguing and indexing
    (<gi>titleStmt</gi>); a statement of how,
    under what authority, and under what license the digital text is
    published (<gi>publicationStmt</gi>), and a
    description of the digital text’s sources
    (<gi>sourceDesc</gi>). </p>
          <div type="level3">
            <head>The title statement</head>
            <p>The title statement supplies the title and author
      <hi rendition="simple:bold">of the digital text</hi>. In most
      cases this will be the same as the title and author
      <hi rendition="simple:bold">of the work</hi>. For example:</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
	
!!!<titleStmt>
  !!!<title>Sarasvatīkaṇṭhābharaṇa!!!</title>
  !!!<author>Bhoja!!!</author>
!!!</titleStmt>
</egXML>
            <p>Very often, however, the SARIT edition will present a work
      along with one or more commentaries (see
      “<ref target="base-texts-and-commentaries">Base texts and
      commentaries</ref>” below). In this case, there are two (or more)
      titles, and two (or more) authors. To reflect the fact that the
      title of the base text will be the main title of the document, we
      use the attributes <att>type</att> and
      <att>subtype</att>, and the authors are distinguished
      by their <att>role</att> attribute, as follows:</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<titleStmt>
  <title type="main" subtype="base-text">Tattvasaṅgraha</title>
  <title type="sub" subtype="commentary">Tattvasaṅgrahapañjikā</title>
  <author role="base-author">Śāntarakṣita</author>
  <author role="commentator">Kamalaśīla</author>
</titleStmt>
	    </egXML>
            <p>In the following example we have a base text and two
      commentaries. When there is only one author for each
      <att>role</att>, it is easy to link authors with the
      titles of their works. But when there are more than one author for
      each role—as is the case with multiple commentaries—we need to
      supply extra an extra <att>n</att> attribute.</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
!!!<titleStmt>
  !!!<title type="main" subtype="base-text">Aṣṭāṅgahṛdayasaṃhitā!!!</title>
  !!!<title type="sub" subtype="commentary" n="1">Sarvāṅgasundarā!!!</title>
  !!!<title type="sub" subtype="commentary" n="2">Āyurvedarasāyana!!!</title>
  !!!<author role="base-author">Vāgbhaṭa!!!</author>
  !!!<author role="commentator" n="1">Aruṇadatta!!!</author>
  !!!<author role="commentator" n="2">Hemādri!!!</author>
!!!</titleStmt>
	    </egXML>
            <p>In addition to providing information about
      <hi rendition="simple:bold">who</hi> produced the work that forms
      the basis of the digital text, namely the author, the title
      statement also provides information about
      <hi rendition="simple:bold">who</hi> helped to produce the digital
      text. This includes funding agencies, principal investigators,
      data enterers, and so on.</p>
            <p>The funding agency and principal investigator have their own
      TEI elements (<gi>funder</gi> and
      <gi>principal</gi>), but it is good practice
      to encode the names of persons with the general-purpose element
      <gi>persName</gi> (further uses of
      <gi>persName</gi> will be discussed in the
      full version of the guidelines):</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
!!!<titleStmt>
  !!!<funder>Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft!!!</funder>
  !!!<funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities!!!</funder>
  !!!<principal>
    !!!<persName>Birgit Kellner!!!</persName>
  !!!</principal>
!!!</titleStmt>
	    </egXML>
            <p>Other responsible parties should be identified with the
      <gi>respStmt</gi>, a “responsibility
      statement” that includes two further elements:
      <gi>resp</gi>, which explains the nature of
      the responsibility, and an element, usually
      <gi>persName</gi>, that identifies the
      responsible party:</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
!!!<titleStmt>
  !!!<respStmt>
    !!!<resp>data entry by!!!</resp>
    !!!<name>SWIFT Information Technologies, Mumbai!!!</name>
  !!!</respStmt>
  !!!<respStmt>
    !!!<resp>prepared for SARIT by!!!</resp>
    !!!<persName>Liudmila Olalde!!!</persName>
  !!!</respStmt>
!!!</titleStmt>
	    </egXML>
            <p/>
          </div>
          <div type="level3">
            <head>The publication statement</head>
            <p>The publication statement tells us how the digital text
      (<hi rendition="simple:bold">not</hi> the sources of the digital
      text) is published. SARIT editions will have a publication
      statement with the following structure, although the TEI P5 
<ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/HD.html#HD24">http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/HD.html#HD24</ref>
      offer additional possibilities:</p>
            <list type="unordered">
              <item>
                <p>the <hi rendition="simple:bold">publisher</hi> of the
          digital text (typically SARIT);</p>
              </item>
              <item>
                <p>its <hi rendition="simple:bold">availability</hi>;</p>
              </item>
              <item>
                <p>the <hi rendition="simple:bold">date</hi> of its
          publication;</p>
              </item>
            </list>
            <p>Texts that are made available through SARIT should include:</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
	
!!!<publisher>SARIT!!!</publisher>
</egXML>
            <p>The availability of a text can either be
      <hi rendition="simple:bold">free</hi> or
      <hi rendition="simple:bold">restricted</hi>, which are the two
      possible values of the attribute <att>status</att> in
      the element <gi>availability</gi>. Unless
      there are special circumstances, SARIT texts are made available
      under a Creative Commons licence. This means that their
      availability is <hi rendition="simple:bold">restricted</hi>, since
      CC licences put restrictions on the further use and reuse of
      documents. (<hi rendition="simple:bold">Free</hi> in this case
      does not refer to cost; all SARIT texts are available free of
      cost.) SARIT texts will therefore usually include a
      <gi>licence</gi> element that either links
      to or reproduces this licence. Here is an example of an element
      that links to the CC license:</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<availability status="restricted">
  <licence>
    <p>Distributed under a
<ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Creative
Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International licence</ref>.
</p>
  </licence>
</availability>
	    </egXML>
            <p>The <hi rendition="simple:bold">date</hi> of publication is
      simply contained in the <gi>date</gi>
      element:</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
	      !!!<date>2014!!!</date>
	    </egXML>
            <p/>
          </div>
          <div type="level3">
            <head>The source description</head>
            <p>The last obligatory portion of the file description is the
      source description, which tells us the sources on which the
      digital text is based. This will often be the most extensive and
      detailed part of the TEI Header. Usually, there will be one
      edition that the digital text is primarily based on. We want to
      distinguish this “main source” from other sources that supplement
      the main source, or “second-level” sources (the sources of the
      digital document’s sources). Thus, by convention, the
      <hi rendition="simple:bold">first</hi> element in the source
      description is understood to be the main source. In order to be
      completely explicit, however, SARIT recommends that the role of
      each source in the constitution of the digital document should be
      briefly explained with a <gi>note</gi>.</p>
            <p>TEI provides a number of ways of tagging bibliographic
      information, but SARIT recommends the use of
      <gi>bibl</gi>. This is a relatively flexible
      element which should accommodate book, articles in journals, and
      articles in collections. The following are examples for different
      kinds of printed sources. The most common is a book, which has one
      or more titles (<gi>title</gi>), one or more
      authors (<gi>author</gi>), usually one or
      more editors (<gi>editor</gi>), and the
      standard publication information
      (<gi>publisher</gi>,
      <gi>pubPlace</gi>, and
      <gi>date</gi>). Note that it is best
      practice to encode <hi rendition="simple:bold">names</hi> of
      modern-day authors and editors using the
      <gi>name</gi> element and its sub-elements,
      <gi>surname</gi> and
      <gi>forename</gi>, in order to make it
      easier to sort and reformat bibliographic entries.</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
	
!!!<bibl>
  !!!<title type="main">Tattvasaṅgraha of Śāntarakṣita With the Commentary of Kamalaśīla.!!!</title>
  !!!<title type="sub">Edited with an Introduction in Sanskrit by Embar Krishnamacharya with a foreword by the general editor. In two volumes!!!</title>
  !!!<author>Śāntarakṣita!!!</author>
  !!!<author>Kamalaśīla!!!</author>
  !!!<editor>
    !!!<name>
  !!!<forename>Embar!!!</forename>
  !!!<surname>Krishnamacharya!!!</surname>
    !!!</name>
  !!!</editor>
  !!!<publisher>Central Library!!!</publisher>
  !!!<pubPlace>Baroda!!!</pubPlace>
  !!!<date>1926!!!</date>
!!!</bibl>
</egXML>            <p>Here is an example for journal articles, demonstrating the use
      of the <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">level</egXML> attribute to distinguish
      between the title of the article (<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">!!!<title
      level="a"/></egXML>) and the title of the journal
      (<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">!!!<title
      level="j"/></egXML>). Note also the use of the
      <gi>biblScope</gi> element to represent a
      page range.</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
	
!!!<sourceDesc>
  !!!<bibl type="article" subtype="journal_article">
    !!!<author>
  !!!<name>
        !!!<forename>Iwata!!!</forename>
        !!!<surname>Takashi!!!</surname>
  !!!</name>
    !!!</author>
    !!!<title level="a">Pramāṇaviniścaya III 64-67: Die Reduzierung richtiger Gründe auf den svabhāva- und kāryahetu!!!</title>
    !!!<title level="j">Wiener Zeitschrift für die Kunde Südasiens!!!</title>
    !!!<date when="1993">1993!!!</date>
    !!!<biblScope unit="pp" from="165" to="200">165-200!!!</biblScope>
  !!!</bibl>
!!!</sourceDesc>
</egXML>            <p>And this is an example of an article in a collection, again
      demonstrating the use of the <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">level</egXML>
      attribute to distinguish between the title of the article
      (<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">!!!<title level="a"/></egXML>) and the
      title of the collection
      (<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">!!!<title level="m"/></egXML> for
      monograph):</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
	
!!!<bibl type="article" subtype="book_chapter">
  !!!<author>
    !!!<name>!!!<forename>Jin-Il!!!</forename>!!!<surname>Chung!!!</surname>!!!</name>
  !!!</author>
  !!!<author>
    !!!<name>!!!<forename>Klaus!!!</forename>!!!<surname>Wille!!!</surname>!!!</name>
  !!!</author>
  !!!<title level="a">Fragmente aus dem Bhaiṣajyavastu der Sarvāstivādins in der Sammlung Pelliot (Paris)!!!</title>
  !!!<title level="m">Sanskrit- Texte aus dem buddhistischen Kanon: Neuentdeckungen und Neueditionen!!!</title>
  !!!<biblScope unit="Folge">4!!!</biblScope>
  !!!<pubPlace>Göttingen!!!</pubPlace>,
  !!!<publisher>Vandenhoeck &amp;amp;amp; Ruprecht!!!</publisher>
  !!!<date when="2003">2003!!!</date>
  !!!<biblScope unit="pp" from="105" to="124">105-124!!!</biblScope>.
  !!!<series>!!!<title level="s"/>!!!<biblScope unit="Beiheft">9!!!</biblScope>!!!</series>
!!!</bibl>
</egXML>            <p>The sources for our printed editions are almost always
      manuscript sources. And when the printed editions refer to these
      manuscript sources, as responsible editions do, it is useful to
      provide a description of the manuscript that readers of the
      digital text will be able to refer to. The proper element for this
      description is <gi>msDesc</gi>, and it is
      contained directly within the
      <gi>sourceDesc</gi> element, alongside any
      bibliographic sources (<gi>bibl</gi>).</p>
            <p>Here is one example:</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
	
!!!<msDesc>
  !!!<msIdentifier xml:id="msK">
    !!!<idno>Kun-de-ling-Manuscript!!!</idno>
  !!!</msIdentifier>
  !!!<msContents>
    !!!<msItem>
  !!!<author>Śāntarakṣita!!!</author>
  !!!<title>Vipañcitārthā!!!</title>
    !!!</msItem>
  !!!</msContents>
  !!!<physDesc>
    !!!<objectDesc>
  !!!<p>Palm-leaf manuscript. 89 leaves in Kuṭilā script. Apparently written in 1152 A.C. !!!</p>
    !!!</objectDesc>
  !!!</physDesc>
  !!!<history>
    !!!<p>In June 1934, Sāṅkṛtyāyana found this manuscript in the monastery of Kun-de-ling (Lhasa). !!!</p>
  !!!</history>
!!!</msDesc>
</egXML>            <p/>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div type="level2">
          <head>The encoding description</head>
          <p>After the file description, TEI documents require an encoding
    description (<gi>encodingDesc</gi>). The
    purpose of the encoding description is to document the choices that
    were made in encoding the text, especially if there may be
    uncertainty or ambiguity, for instance regarding how the different
    layers of base text and commentary are represented in the TEI
    document.</p>
          <p><hi rendition="simple:bold">At the moment SARIT provides no
    specific guidelines for the encoding description.</hi> The
    <gi>encodingDesc</gi> element of SARIT texts
    generally consists of prose paragraphs
    (<gi>p</gi>) that explain the encoding choices
    specific to the text. There should be no need of noting encoding
    decisions that conform to these guidelines. We do, however,
    recommend the use of three elements that are available in the
    encoding description: <gi>projectDesc</gi>,
    <gi>tagsDecl</gi>, and
    <gi>refsDecl</gi>.</p>
          <p>The project description
    (<gi>projectDesc</gi>) is a paragraph or two
    that describes the project or projects which resulted in the
    creation of the digital text:</p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
	
!!!<projectDesc>
  !!!<p>Producing as part of the NEH-DFG project “Enriching Digital Texts Collections in Indology” from 2012 to 2015.!!!</p>
!!!</projectDesc>
</egXML>          <p>The tagging declaration (<gi>tagsDecl</gi>)
    may be used to document the usage of specific tags in the text and
    their rendition if applicable (see the TEI P5 guidelines: <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/HD.html#HD57">http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/HD.html#HD57</ref>).
    Most projects will not use the tagging declaration.</p>
          <p>The reference declaration
    (<gi>refsDecl</gi>), however, is important: it
    describes the reference system used in the text. It may be a pattern
    of canonical references (see the full guidelines for more details),
    or it may simply describe the structure of the text in English
    prose, as follows:</p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
	
!!!<refsDecl>
  !!!<p>References in this text are either in the format w.x.z or w.x.y.z.!!!</p>
  !!!<p>w represents the !!!<att>n!!!</att> attribute of the highest-level
!!!<gi>div!!!</gi> element (an adhyāya).!!!</p>
  !!!<p>x represents the !!!<att>n!!!</att> attribute of the second-highest-level
!!!<gi>div!!!</gi> element (a pāda).!!!</p>
  !!!<p>y represents the !!!<att>n!!!</att> attribute of the third-highest-level
!!!<gi>div!!!</gi> element (an adhikaraṇa).!!!</p>
  !!!<p>z represents the !!!<att>n!!!</att> attribute of the fourth-highest-level
!!!<gi>div!!!</gi> element, which contains the text of a sūtra along with
any portion of the commentary that specifically concerns that
sūtra.!!!</p>
!!!</refsDecl>
</egXML>          <p/>
        </div>
        <div type="level2">
          <head>The revision description</head>
          <p>This is the last obligatory portion of the TEI header. It
    consists of a number of <gi>change</gi>
    elements, each of which has a <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">who</egXML> and a
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">when</egXML> attribute. The
    <gi>change</gi> elements will typically
    include a list of changes, as below (note that
    <gi>list</gi> should be a child of
    <gi>change</gi>, not
    <gi>revisionDesc</gi>):</p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
	
!!!<revisionDesc>
  !!!<change who="lo" when="2014-10-29">
    !!!<list>
  !!!<item>I corrected folio number 46b to 49b on p. 73.!!!</item>
  !!!<item>I added folio number 53b, which was missing in the printed edition.!!!</item>
    !!!</list>
  !!!</change>
!!!</revisionDesc>
</egXML>          <p>Prose paragraphs (<gi>p</gi>) are also permitted in !!!<gi>change</gi>
    elements, but lists are preferred.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="level1">
        <head>Base texts and commentaries</head>
        <p/>
        <p>The rest of these guidelines will concern the text’s data rather
  than its metadata. All of this data is contained in the element
  <gi>text</gi> that immediately follows the TEI
  Header. The <gi>text</gi> element must contain a
  <gi>body</gi> element which represents the body
  of the text; it might also contain
  <gi>front</gi> and
  <gi>back</gi> elements, representing any front
  matter or back matter, respectively. The
  <gi>text</gi> element must also have an
  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">xml:lang</egXML> attribute that tells us what language
  and what script the text contained therein is written in. Here is an
  example for a text encoded in Roman transliteration:</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
	
!!!<text xml:lang="sa-Latn">
  !!!<body>
....
!!!</body>
!!!</text>
</egXML>        <p>And an example for a text encoded in Devanāgarī:</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
	
!!!<text xml:lang="sa-Deva">
  !!!<body>
....
!!!</body>
!!!</text>
</egXML>        <p>The <gi>text</gi> element is the last child
  element of <gi>TEI</gi>.</p>
        <p>A single document might contain more than one text. In particular,
  a single document will very often contain a commentary together with
  the text that it is a commentary on, hence known as the “base text.”
  You may only be interested in the base text, or only in the
  commentary. But you may also want to encode
  <hi rendition="simple:bold">both</hi> texts, and in that case you will
  also want to make the relationship between the texts explicit. There
  are, in general, two options for encoding a base text with its
  commentary:</p>
        <list type="unordered">
          <item>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:bold">Together</hi>. The base text and
      the commentary are encoded in a single</p>
          </item>
        </list>
        <p>document.</p>
        <list type="unordered">
          <item>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:bold">Separate</hi>. The base text and
      the commentary are encoded in separate</p>
          </item>
        </list>
        <p>documents. They are linked to each other (i.e., the commentary
  includes references to the base text) through the procedures described
  in the full version of the guidelines.</p>
        <p>For example, SARIT includes a text of the
  <hi rendition="simple:bold">Daśarūpaka</hi> of Dhanañjaya, together
  with the <hi rendition="simple:bold">Avaloka</hi> commentary by
  Dhanañjaya’s brother Dhanika. These two texts are encoded in a single
  document. A further commentary on the two texts, the
  <hi rendition="simple:bold">Laghuṭīkā</hi> of Bhaṭṭa Nṛsiṃha, is
  encoded in a separate document that refers back to the original
  document.</p>
        <p>Generally speaking, if the base text and commentary are printed in
  the same register on the page (the base text being in a larger font or
  in bold, see below example 1), it makes sense to encode them together;
  if the base text and commentary are printed in separate registers (see
  below example 2), it is easier to encode them separately.</p>
        <p>These guidelines will tell you how to encode the base text and the
  commentary <hi rendition="simple:bold">together</hi>. Please consult
  the full version for guidance on how to encode them
  <hi rendition="simple:bold">separately</hi>.</p>
        <p>
          <hi rendition="simple:bold">Example 1</hi>
        </p>
        <p>
          <figure>
            <head>Base text embedded in commentary</head>
            <graphic url="~/webstuff/sarit-webapp/exist-things/sarit-pm/resources/img/ex-embedded-base-pvv.jpg"/>
            <figDesc>fig:</figDesc>
          </figure>
        </p>
        <p>
          <hi rendition="simple:bold">Example 2</hi>
        </p>
        <p>
          <figure>
            <head>"base text and commentary"</head>
            <graphic url="~/webstuff/sarit-webapp/exist-things/sarit-pm/resources/img/ex-base-text_commentary.jpg"/>
            <figDesc>fig:</figDesc>
          </figure>
        </p>
        <p/>
        <div type="level2">
          <head>The base text is a quotation</head>
          <p>SARIT recommends a model in which the base text is “embedded” in
    the commentary. In other words, we presume that everything in the
    !!!<gi>text</gi> element represents the commentary
    <hi rendition="simple:bold">unless specified otherwise</hi>. The
    rest of this section will deal with how to specify otherwise.</p>
          <p>When a base text is included or embedded within a commentary,
    SARIT treats it as a special kind of
    <hi rendition="simple:bold">quotation</hi>. It should therefore be
    enclosed within the tag <gi>quote</gi>, which
    TEI uses for quoted material, and this tag will have the attribute
    ~type="base-text"~. Theoretically we should be able to
    extract the base text from the commentary by pulling out all of the
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><quote type="base-text"/></egXML> elements. In the following
    example the verse आनन्दनिष्यन्दिषु etc. is marked as belonging to
    the base text, because it is contained within the <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><quote
    type="base-text"/></egXML> element:</p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
	
!!!<div>
  !!!<p>इदं प्रकरणं दशरूपज्ञानफलम् । दशरूपज्ञानं किंफलमित्याह—!!!</p>
  !!!<quote type="base-text">
    !!!<lg n="6">
  !!!<l>आनन्दनिष्यन्दिषु रूपकेषु व्युत्पत्तिमात्रं फलमल्पबुद्धिः ।!!!</l>
  !!!<l>योऽपीतिहासादिवदाह साधुस्तस्मै नमः स्वादपराङ्मुखाय ॥!!!</l>
    !!!</lg>
  !!!</quote>
!!!</div>
</egXML>          <p>As in the above example, we recommend making the
    <gi>quote</gi> element that contains the base
    text a <hi rendition="simple:bold">sibling</hi> rather than a
    <hi rendition="simple:bold">child</hi> of the elements of the
    commentary (<gi>p</gi> and so on). That is,
    the <gi>quote</gi> element should be a child
    of the same structural division (see below) as the elements of the
    commentary. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="level2">
          <head>Enclose the base text and commentary in a division</head>
          <p>In almost every case, the structure of the base text and
    commentary will be the same. This means that a given reference, such
    as 1.4.5, should be able to identify both the base text and the
    corresponding section of commentary. The easiest way to accomplish
    this is to <hi rendition="simple:bold">put the base text and the
    corresponding section of commentary within a single structural
    division</hi>. This enclosing division is meant to gather the two
    texts together for the purposes of display and reference.</p>
          <p>The “section of a commentary” that corresponds to a section of
    the base text will often take the form of an optional
    <hi rendition="simple:bold">avataraṇikā</hi>, the base text, and
    then a more extensive commentary. This should all be enclosed within
    a <gi>div</gi> element, as follows:</p>
          <p>
            <hi rendition="simple:bold">Example 3</hi>
          </p>
          <p>
            <figure>
              <head>"div: base text and comentary"</head>
              <graphic url="~/webstuff/sarit-webapp/exist-things/sarit-pm/resources/img/ex-base-text-commentary-div3.jpg"/>
              <figDesc>fig:</figDesc>
            </figure>
          </p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<div n="249">
  <p>स्वसम्वेदनमाख्यातुमाह (।)</p>
  <quote type="base-text">
    <lg n="249">
  <l>अशक्यसमयो ह्यात्मा रागादीनामनन्यभाक् ।</l>
  <l>तेषामतः स्वसंवित्तिर्न्नाभिजल्पानुषङ्गिणी ॥ २४९ ॥</l>
    </lg>
  </quote>
  <p>रागद्वेषसुखदुःखादीनां सर्व्वचित्तचैत्तानामात्मसंवेदनं प्रत्यक्षमविकल्पत्वात् ।</p>
  <p>तथा हि । ... न शब्दसंगतः । (२४९)</p>
</div>

</egXML>          <p>Note that an <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">n</egXML> attribute is assigned to
    the enclosing division. This is optional, but it helps to identify
    the section of the commentary with the verse-number of the base text
    that it comments upon (which is identical with the
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">n</egXML> attribute of the quoted
    <gi>lg</gi> element). The enclosing division
    may also have a <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">type</egXML> attribute, such as
    ~type="sūtra"~, which tells us that it gathers the portion
    of the commentary that concerns a given sūtra. This attribute, too,
    is optional.</p>
          <p>Here is an example without an
    <hi rendition="simple:bold">avataraṇikā</hi>:</p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
	
!!!<div n="7">
  !!!<quote type="base-text">
    !!!<lg n="7">
  !!!<l>अशेषशक्तिप्रचितात्प्रधानादेव केवलात् ।!!!</l>
  !!!<l>कार्यभेदाः प्रवर्त्तन्ते तद्रूपा एव भावतः ॥ ७ ॥!!!</l>
    !!!</lg>
  !!!</quote>
  !!!<p>यदशेषाभिर्महदादिकार्यग्रामजनिकाभिरात्मभूताभिः शक्तिभिः, प्रचितम्—युक्तं सत्वरजस्तमसां साम्यावस्थालक्षणं प्रधानम्, तत एवैते महदादयः कार्यभेदाः प्रवर्त्तन्ते इति कापिलाः । ...!!!</p>
!!!</div>
</egXML>          <p/>
        </div>
        <div type="level2">
          <head>Several sections of the base text corresponding to one section
    of commentary</head>
          <p>It may be the case that a commentary will skip one section of the
    base text, or comment on several sections of the base text at the
    same time. In such cases, the enclosing division will simply include
    more than one section of the base text. The label
    (<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">n</egXML>) for this division will include all of the
    sections of the base text that are comprised in the division. For
    example, a section of commentary that comments upon two sūtras of
    the base text:</p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">

<div n="10 11" type="sūtra">
  <quote type="base-text">
    <ab n="10" type="sūtra">प्रकृतिविकृत्योश्च ॥</ab>
    <ab n="11" type="sūtra">वृद्धिश्च कर्तृभूम्नास्य ॥</ab>
  </quote>
  <p>प्रकृतिविकारभावञ्च शब्दज्ञाः स्मरन्ति ; न चायं नित्यस्योपपद्यते ; तस्मात् स्मृतिरपि पूर्वोक्तहेत्वनुगुणैव । सादृश्यमप्यनुगुणमुपलभामह इत्युपपन्नं कार्यत्वम् ॥</p>
</div>

</egXML>          <p>
            <hi rendition="simple:bold">Example 4</hi>
          </p>
          <p>
            <figure>
              <head><gi>quote</gi> for base text</head>
              <graphic url="~/webstuff/sarit-webapp/exist-things/sarit-pm/resources/img/ex-embedded-base-text2.jpg"/>
              <figDesc>fig:</figDesc>
            </figure>
          </p>
          <p/>
        </div>
        <div type="level2">
          <head>Sections of commentary that don’t correspond to any section of
    the base text</head>
          <p>Commentaries sometimes have material that doesn’t correspond to a
    particular section of the base text: the most common example is
    introductory material. This material, too, must be put in an
    enclosing division; the only difference is that this division will
    not contain any base text elements.</p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
	
!!!<div>
  !!!<lg>
    !!!<l>सृष्टाविद्यानिशाध्वंसिनिबन्धमयवासरम् ।!!!</l>
    !!!<l>उज्जासितजगज्जाड्यं नमस्यामः प्रभाकरम् ॥ १ ॥!!!</l>
  !!!</lg>
  !!!<lg>
    !!!<l>प्रभाकरमयीं दृष्टिं दक्षिणां दधतं सदा ।!!!</l>
    !!!<l>वामदर्शनतापन्नचन्द्रं वन्देऽपराजितम् ॥ २ ॥!!!</l>
  !!!</lg>
  !!!<lg>
    !!!<l>प्रभाकरगुरोर्भावमतिगम्भीरभाषिणः ।!!!</l>
    !!!<l>अञ्जसा व्यञ्जयिष्यन्ती पञ्चिका क्रियते मया ॥ ३ ॥!!!</l>
  !!!</lg>
  !!!<lg>
    !!!<l>उपन्यासनिरासाभ्यां व्यासेनैषा विदूषिता ।!!!</l>
    !!!<l>व्याख्या प्राचां निबन्धॄणामिति नाहमदूदुषम् ॥ ४ ॥!!!</l>
  !!!</lg>
!!!</div>
</egXML>          <p/>
        </div>
        <div type="level2">
          <head>Sections of base text that are distributed across several
    sections of commentary</head>
          <p>Sometimes what we think of as a single section of the base text
    (a verse, paragraph, etc.) is split up between several sections of
    commentary: for example, the commentary might take individual words
    from the base text in turn. Although the underlying principle is the
    same—put the base text elements within an enclosing division that
    also includes the commentary—the base text elements in this case
    will be fragmented, and we need to provide enough information to
    allow the structure of the base text to be reconstituted. Thus the
    elements of the base text should be labelled as specified below (in
    the “verse fragments” section).</p>
          <p/>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="level1">
        <head>Sections of the text</head>
        <p>There are many Sanskrit words for sections of a text: sarga,
  adhyāya, aṅka, pariccheda, ucchvāsa, etc. The encoding of these
  sections should meet several requirements:</p>
        <list type="unordered">
          <item>
            <p>the XML document itself should be valid;</p>
          </item>
          <item>
            <p>the structure of the XML document reflects the logical
      structure of the text;</p>
          </item>
          <item>
            <p>a standard reference system should be able to use the structure
      of the XML document</p>
          </item>
        </list>
        <p>as a proxy for the structure of the text;</p>
        <list type="unordered">
          <item>
            <p>texts in the corpus are broadly consistent in the encoding
      strategy used for these</p>
          </item>
        </list>
        <p>sections.</p>
        <p>These considerations lead us to recommend the use of
  <gi>div</gi> for all "parts,"
  "sections," and "divisions" in the text, whatever
  their Sanskrit name is, and at whatever depth they occur. Do
  <hi rendition="simple:bold">not</hi> use the numbered divisions
  available in earlier versions of the TEI Guidelines
  (<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">!!!<div1/></egXML>,
  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">!!!<div2/></egXML>, etc.).</p>
        <p>Before encoding a text, you should figure out a strategy for
  representing all of the relevant levels of the text as
  <gi>div</gi> elements. Some Mīmāṃsā texts, for
  example, are organized according to the hierarchical organization of
  the Mīmāṃsā Sūtras into adhyāyas, pādas, and adhikaraṇas. The first
  <gi>div</gi> beneath the
  <gi>body</gi> element
  (<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">body/div</egXML>) will thus correspond to an adhyāya,
  the first <gi>div</gi> below this to a pāda
  (<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">body/div/div</egXML>), and the first
  <gi>div</gi> below this
  (<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">body/div/div/div</egXML>) to an adhikaraṇa. If this
  schema is applied consistently, there is no need for assigning a type
  to the <gi>div</gi> elements themselves (e.g.,
  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">!!!<div type="adhyāya"/></egXML>,
  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">!!!<div
  type="pāda"/></egXML>,
  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">!!!<div type="adhikaraṇa"/></egXML>), but
  these <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">type</egXML> attributes may be included in order
  to make the XML easier to read.</p>
        <p>The strategy followed in the text can be, and should be, documented
  in the reference declaration
  (<gi>refsDecl</gi>), which is part of the
  encoding description (<gi>encodingDesc</gi>) in
  the TEI Header (see above). </p>
        <div type="level2">
          <head>Labelling sections</head>
          <p>Sections of the text should be
    <hi rendition="simple:bold">identifiable</hi>. In order to be
    identifiable to humans, sections generally carry a heading and/or a
    trailer (see below). In order to be identifiable to machines,
    sections carry a numeric <hi rendition="simple:bold">label</hi> that
    is represented by the <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">n</egXML> attribute of the
    corresponding <gi>div</gi> element. The value
    of <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">@n</egXML> will usually be the serial number of
    the section: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">!!!<div
    n="2"/></egXML> represents the second division (adhyāya,
    pāda, adhikaraṇa, etc.), even if it's not actually the second
    <gi>div</gi> element within its parent
    element. For division that comprises more than one such section, we
    simply put all of the corresponding numbers in the
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">n</egXML> attribute:
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">!!!<div n="2 3
    4"/></egXML>.</p>
          <p>Divisions (!!!<gi>div</gi>s) are block-level elements, and they
    constitute the text hierarchy, together with other block-level
    elements like paragraphs (<gi>p</gi>), verses
    (<gi>lg</gi>), and the “anonymous blocks” used
    for sūtras and the like (<gi>ab</gi>). The
    overall reference system of the text will therefore usually include
    the numbering of <gi>div</gi> elements at the
    upper levels and the numbering of <gi>lg</gi>
    or <gi>ab</gi> elements at the lower levels.
    </p>
        </div>
        <div type="level2">
          <head>Headings and trailers</head>
          <p>Headings and trailers are short “paratexts” that announce the
    beginning or end of a section. These may be original to the text, or
    added by scribes or even the editor: the general rule, however, is
    that if it is included in the printed text, it should be included in
    the digital text; if you determine that the editor or a scribe was
    in fact responsible for adding some or all of these “paratexts,” TEI
    allows you to hold him responsible and ultimately filter out such
    interventions if desired. See “holding people responsible” in the
    SARIT Full guidelines. </p>
          <div type="level3">
            <head>Headings</head>
            <p>Some sections of the text will begin with a heading, most often
      a short introductory phrase (e.g., अथ भावाधिकरणम्). We encode
      these heading with the TEI element
      <gi>head</gi>. There can be more than one
      <gi>head</gi> element at the beginning of a
      section:</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
	
!!!<text xml:lang="sa-Deva">
  !!!<body>!!!<head>श्रीः!!!</head>!!!<head>अभिनवभारती!!!</head>
...
!!!</body>
!!!</text>
</egXML>            <p>In addition to the headings printed in the text, the heading
      element is a convenient place to put chapter or section titles for
      a table of contents, especially if there are no printed headings,
      or if they would be unsuitable for a table of contents. This is
      also a way to use English or transliterated titles within a
      Sanskrit text (using, of course, the relevant
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">xml:lang</egXML> attribute). You are therefore
      encouraged to use the special element
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">!!!<head type="toc"/></egXML>, which
      will supply the title of the section in question to the table of
      contents, but which is itself suppressed in the browsing display
      on the SARIT website. For example:</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
	
!!!<div n="1">!!!<head>अथ प्रथमपरिच्छेदः!!!</head>!!!<head type="toc" xml:lang="en">First chapter!!!</head>
...
!!!</div>
</egXML>            <p/>
          </div>
          <div type="level3">
            <head>Trailers</head>
            <p>SARIT uses the TEI element
      <gi>trailer</gi> for those short pieces of
      text (often called colophons) that come at the end of a section.
      <gi>trailer</gi> should typically be the
      final element in the element that it closes.</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
	      <trailer>॥ इति बृहत्यां प्रथमाध्यायस्य प्रथमः पादः समाप्तः ॥</trailer>
	    </egXML>
            <p>
              <hi rendition="simple:bold">Example 5</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
              <figure>
                <head>"Trailers"</head>
                <graphic url="~/webstuff/sarit-webapp/exist-things/sarit-pm/resources/img/ex-trailer.jpg"/>
                <figDesc>fig:</figDesc>
              </figure>
            </p>
          </div>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="level1">
        <head>Milestones</head>
        <p>SARIT recommends encoding the page and, where possible, line
  numbers of the source edition for purposes of reference. (The digital
  text will have its own lineation and pagination depending on the media
  in which it is viewed.) These are encoded as “milestone” elements,
  that is, single elements that mark the transition from one unit to the
  text. Sometimes other kinds of milestones besides lines and pages are
  noted in source editions, for example manuscript folios. Specific
  guidelines for the use of these elements are provided below. </p>
        <div type="level2">
          <head>Lines</head>
          <p><hi rendition="simple:bold">If you choose to encode line-breaks
    at all, every single line-break of the source edition must be
    explicitly represented in the digital texts.</hi> Whenever a new
    line begins in the source edition, the element
    <gi>lb</gi> must appear, whether it occurs
    within a prose paragraph, or at the end of a prose paragraph; within
    a metrical line of verse, or at the end of such a line. If
    line-breaks are encoded consistently, there is no need to assign
    them a numeric label, because the line-number can be automatically
    determined</p>
          <p>The <gi>lb</gi> element is assumed to
    refer to line-breaks in the principal source of the digital text.
    (If you wish to encode line-breaks of another edition, use the
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">ed</egXML> attribute to refer to it, and see the
    section on internal references in the full version of the
    guidelines.)</p>
          <p>SARIT distinguishes two types of line breaks:
          <list type="unordered">
            <item>
              <p>a <gi>lb</gi> between words: e.g.,
              <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">उक्तं <lb/>च</egXML></p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p>a <gi>lb</gi> in the middle of a
              word, and thus after an end-of-line
              hyphen. SARIT uses the <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">break</egXML> attribute to
    specify that the element "is considered not to mark the end of
    any adjacent orthographic token"; the hyphen itself is
    <hi rendition="simple:bold">not</hi> encoded. For example:
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">शं!!!<lb
    break="no"/>करः</egXML></p>
            </item>
	  </list>
	  </p>
	<p>
            <hi rendition="simple:bold">Example 6</hi>
          </p>
          <p>
            <figure>
              <head><gi>lb</gi> and <gi>pb</gi></head>
              <graphic url="~/webstuff/sarit-webapp/exist-things/sarit-pm/resources/img/ex-lbs-and-pbs-3pvv.jpg"/>
              <figDesc>fig:</figDesc>
            </figure>
          </p>
          <p>
            <hi rendition="simple:bold">Example 7</hi>
          </p>
          <p>
            <figure>
              <head>"lb and pb"</head>
              <graphic url="~/webstuff/sarit-webapp/exist-things/sarit-pm/resources/img/ex-lbs-and-pbs-4vnt.jpg"/>
              <figDesc>fig:</figDesc>
            </figure>
          </p>
          <p/>
        </div>
        <div type="level2">
          <head>Pages</head>
          <p>The pagination of the source edition is encoded by placing the
    element <gi>pb</gi> (for "page
    break") at the beginning of every new page. In contrast to
    line-breaks, SARIT requires the <gi>pb</gi>
    element to have a numeric label (<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">n</egXML>) that
    corresponds to the page number. But like line-breaks, SARIT uses the
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">break</egXML> attribute to distinguish between page
    breaks that occur between words (e.g.,
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">उपपन्नम् । !!!<pb n="2"/>यदि च</egXML>)
    and page breaks that occur within a word (e.g.,
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">उपप!!!<pb n="2"
    break="no"/>न्नम् । यदि च</egXML>). And also like
    line-breaks, we assume that the breaking element and the
    corresponding number refer by default to the principal source
    edition. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="level2">
          <head>Folios</head>
          <p>Manuscript folios are treated as pages, so the beginning of a new
    manuscript folio (or a new side of a manuscript folio) is encoded
    with the <gi>pb</gi> element. These elements
    have an <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">@ed</egXML> attribute that refers to the
    manuscript (the manuscript itself should be mentioned in the source
    description of the TEI header).</p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
	
!!!<pb ed="msK" n="2a"/>
</egXML>          <p/>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="level1">
        <head>Prose</head>
        <p>Prose paragraphs should be encoded using TEI’s <gi>p</gi>
	element.</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
	  <p>देवमुनिगुरुनृपपुत्रविषया तु भाव एव न पुना रसः ।!!!</p>
	</egXML>
        <p/>
      </div>
      <div type="level1">
        <head>Verse</head>
        <p>SARIT uses the <gi>lg</gi> element, a “line
  group,” for metrical verses. A verse contains a number of metrical
  <hi rendition="simple:bold">lines</hi>, which are encoded with the
  <gi>l</gi> element. You can think of a
  <hi rendition="simple:bold">line</hi> in the context of verse as
  anything that ends in a daṇḍa or a double daṇḍa. The only elements
  permitted in the <gi>lg</gi> element are line
  elements (<gi>l</gi>) and labels
  (<gi>label</gi>), besides milestone elements
  (<gi>pb</gi> and
  <gi>lb</gi>). Verses that are numbered in the
  edition should also be given a label (<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">n</egXML>) by
  which they can be easily identified. Generally the verse numbers in
  the printed text, however, should also be represented as text. That
  is, the number of the verse is included both in the
  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">n</egXML> attribute of the verse element
  <gi>lg</gi>, and at the end of the second line,
  as follows:</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
	
!!!<lg n="1">
  !!!<l>वागर्थाविव संपृक्तौ वागर्थप्रतिपत्तये ।!!!</l>
  !!!<l>जगतः पितरौ वन्दे पार्वतीपरमेश्वरौ ॥ १ ॥!!!</l>
!!!</lg>
</egXML>        <p><hi rendition="simple:bold">Metrical lines are not typographic
  lines</hi>. A typographic line break, encoded as
  <gi>lb</gi>, might occur in the middle of, or
  at the end of, a metrical line. A metrical line usually consists of
  two metrical quarters (pādas), and thus a verse usually consists of
  four quarters. The juncture between two quarters is a kind of break or
  pause, and therefore we encode it using the TEI element
  <gi>caesura</gi>.</p>
        <p>Why do we use both <gi>caesura</gi> and
  <gi>lb</gi>? The
  <gi>caesura</gi> element encodes an element of
  metrical structure that often motivates or explains the way the verse
  has been set on the page in the source edition. The
  <gi>lb</gi> element may thus coincide with a
  <gi>caesura</gi> element, but its primary
  purpose is to <hi rendition="simple:bold">count the number of line
  breaks on a page</hi>. For example, a digital text that does not
  render line-breaks at all might encode the following verse:</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
	
!!!<lg>
  !!!<l>स्वसुखनिरभिलाषः खिद्यसे लोकहेतोः!!!<caesura/> प्रतिदिनमथवा ते वृत्तिरेवंविधैव ।!!!</l>
  !!!<l>अनुभवति हि मूर्ध्ना पादपस्तीव्रमुष्णं!!!<caesura/> शमयति परितापं छाययोपाश्रितानाम् ॥!!!</l>
!!!</lg>
</egXML>        <p>The lineation of the source edition does not always reflect this
  structure. Here is one possible representation:</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
	
!!!<lg>
  !!!<l>स्वसुखनिरभिलाषः खिद्यसे !!!<lb/>
लोकहेतोः!!!<caesura/> प्रतिदिनमथवा ते वृत्तिरेवंविधैव ।!!!</l>
  !!!<l>अनुभवति हि मूर्ध्ना पादपस्तीव्रमुष्णं!!!<caesura/>!!!<lb/>
शमयति परितापं छाययोपाश्रितानाम् ॥!!!</l>
!!!</lg>
</egXML>        <p>When the line is broken in the middle of a word, use the
  ~break="no"~ attribute rather than hard-coding a hyphen into
  the text, as noted in the section on milestones above:</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
	
!!!<lg>
  !!!<l>तिष्ठन् भाति पितुः पुरो भुवि यथा सिंहासने किं तथा!!!<caesura/>!!!<lb/>यत् संवाहयतः सुखं हि चरणौ तातस्य किं राज्यतः ।!!!</l>
  !!!<l>किं भुक्ते भुवनत्रये धृतिरसौ भुक्तोज्झिते या गुरो!!!<caesura/>!!!<lb break="no"/>रायासः खलु राज्यमुज्झितगुरोस्तत्रास्ति कश्चिद् गुणः ॥!!!</l>
!!!</lg>
</egXML>        <p>The common <hi rendition="simple:bold">āryā</hi> meter and its
  relatives call for some comment: they are sometimes thought of as
  having four quarters, and sometimes not. SARIT recommends the use of
  the <gi>caesura</gi> element to represent the
  <hi rendition="simple:bold">yati</hi> between the first and second
  half of the line, when it is present; when the
  <hi rendition="simple:bold">yati</hi> is absent, the
  <gi>caesura</gi> element may be omitted. For
  example:</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
	
!!!<lg n="87">
  !!!<l>हुअवह-पडित्त-णूमिअ-!!!<caesura/>णिअ-णणुम्हा-विसंठुल-मह-ग्गाहं ।!!!</l>
  !!!<l>परिवड्ढिएक्कमेक्काणुराअ-सर-पहर-णिव्वलिअ-सङ्ख-उलं ॥ ८७ ॥!!!</l>
!!!</lg>
</egXML>        <p/>
        <div type="level2">
          <head>Groups of verses</head>
          <p>Groups of verses should simply be put into another
    <gi>lg</gi> element that encloses the
    <gi>lg</gi> elements corresponding to
    individual verses. If there is a label for the group in the printed
    text (e.g., kulaka, yugalaka, etc.), it should be included with the
    <gi>label</gi> element, as follows:</p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
	
!!!<lg>
  !!!<label>जुग्गं!!!</label>
  !!!<lg n="34">
    !!!<l>इअ पहसिअ-कुमुअ-सरे !!!<caesura/>भडि-मुह-पङ्क-विरुद्ध-चन्दालोए ।!!!</l>
    !!!<l>जाए फुरन्त-तारे !!!<caesura/>लच्छि-संगाह-णव-पोसे सरे ॥ ३४ ॥!!!</l>
  !!!</lg>
  !!!<lg n="35">
    !!!<l>झिज्जइ झीणा वि तणू !!!<caesura/>अट्ठिअ-बाहं पुणो परुण्णं व मुहं ।!!!</l>
    !!!<l>रामस्स अईसन्ते !!!<caesura/>आसा-बन्धे व्व चिर-गे हणुमन्ते ॥ ३५ ॥!!!</l>
  !!!</lg>
!!!</lg>
</egXML>          <p/>
        </div>
        <div type="level2">
          <head>Fragments of verses</head>
          <p>Sometimes the parts of a verse are broken up within a text, for
    example when a commentator breaks up a verse to discuss its
    components separately. In these cases, every verse-fragment should
    be contained in an <gi>lg</gi> element with
    the attributes <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">next</egXML>,
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">prev</egXML>, or both.</p>
          <p>All of the verse-fragments should have an identifying label (a,
    b, c, etc.), e.g.
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">n="27c"~. The value of ~next</egXML> and
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">prev</egXML> should refer to these identifying
    labels, e.g., ~next="27d"~.</p>
          <p>The labelling convention will allow applications to identify
    “verse 27” as the sum of its parts in case there is no element
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">!!!<lg n="27"/></egXML> to be found.
    However, it will not join fragmentary
    <gi>l</gi> elements into a single element.
    Therefore it is recommended to use the <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">part</egXML>
    attribute on any fragmentary <gi>l</gi>
    attributes: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">I</egXML> for an initial fragment (e.g.,
    pādas a or c) and <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">F</egXML> for a final fragment
    (e.g., pādas b or d), or <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">M</egXML> for a medial
    fragment if such a case occurs.</p>
          <p>
            <hi rendition="simple:bold">Example 8</hi>
          </p>
          <p>
            <hi rendition="simple:italic">~/webstuff/eXist-stuff/sarit-pm/resources/img//part-img1-coloured.png</hi>
          </p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
	
!!!<div>
  !!!<div type="section" n="27c">
    !!!<p>!!!<hi>परिन्यास!!!</hi>माह—!!!</p>
    !!!<quote type="base-text">
  !!!<lg n="27c" prev="27b" next="27d">
        !!!<l part="I">
तन्निष्पत्तिः परिन्यासो
!!!</l>
  !!!</lg>
    !!!</quote>
    !!!<p>
यथा तत्रैव !!!<note>(रत्ना॰ १।८)!!!</note>—
!!!<lg>!!!<l>प्रारम्भेऽस्मिन् स्वामिनो वृद्धिहेतौ दैवे चेत्थं दत्तहस्तावलम्बने ।!!!</l>!!!<l>सिद्धेर्भ्रान्तिर्नास्ति सत्यं तथापि स्वेच्छाकारी भीत एवास्मि भर्तुः ॥!!!</l>!!!</lg>
इत्यनेन यौगन्धरायणः स्वव्यापारस्य दैवयोगात् निष्पत्तिमुक्तवानिति परिन्यासः ।
!!!</p>
  !!!</div>
  !!!<!-- section -->
  !!!<div type="section" n="27d">
    !!!<p>!!!<term>विलोभन!!!</term>माह—!!!</p>
    !!!<quote type="base-text">
  !!!<lg n="27d" prev="27c">
        !!!<l part="F">
गुणाख्यानाद् विलोभनम् ॥ २७ ॥
!!!</l>
  !!!</lg>
    !!!</quote>
  !!!</div>
  !!!<!-- section -->
!!!</div>
</egXML>          <p>
            <hi rendition="simple:bold">Example 9</hi>
          </p>
          <p>
            <figure>
              <head>"fragments of verses"</head>
              <graphic url="~/webstuff/sarit-webapp/exist-things/sarit-pm/resources/img/ex-base-text-commentary-div2.jpg"/>
              <figDesc>fig:</figDesc>
            </figure>
          </p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
	
!!!<div n="210">
  !!!<quote type="base-text">
    !!!<lg n="210a" next="210b">
  !!!<l>किं स्यात् सा चित्रतैकस्यां;!!!</l>
    !!!</lg>
  !!!</quote>
  !!!<p>ननु यदि सा चित्रता बुद्धावेकस्यां स्यात् तया च चित्रमेकं द्रव्यं व्यवस्थाप्येत (।) तदा कि दूषणं स्यात् ।!!!</p>
  !!!<p>आह (।)!!!</p>
  !!!<quote type="base-text">
    !!!<lg n="210b" prev="210a" next="210c">
  !!!<l>न स्यात्तस्यां मतावपि ।!!!</l>
    !!!</lg>
  !!!</quote>
  !!!<p>न केवलं द्रव्ये तस्यां मतावप्येकस्यां न स्या च्चित्रता । आकारनानात्वलक्षणत्वाद् भेदस्य । नानात्वेपि चित्रता कथम् (।) अनेकपुरुषप्रतीतिवत् ।!!!</p>
  !!!<p>कथन्तर्हि प्रतीतिरित्याह (।)!!!</p>
  !!!<quote type="base-text">
    !!!<lg n="210c" prev="210b">
  !!!<l>यदीदं स्वयमर्थानां रोचते तत्र के वयम् ॥ २१० ॥!!!</l>
    !!!</lg>
  !!!</quote>
  !!!<p>!!!<q>यदीद!!!</q>मताद्रूप्येपि ताद्रूप्यप्रथनमर्थानां भासमानानां नीलादीनां स्वयमपरप्रेरणया रोचते । तत्र तथाप्रतिभासे के वयमसहमानाऽ(? अ) पि निषेद्धुं । अवस्तु च प्रतिभासते चेति व्यक्तमालीक्यं । (२१०)!!!</p>
!!!</div>
</egXML>          <p/>
        </div>
        <div type="level2">
          <head>Verses within prose paragraphs</head>
          <p>Often verses are “embedded” into paragraphs, and we reflect this
    fact by embedding the <gi>lg</gi> element into
    the <gi>p</gi> element.</p>
          <p/>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="level1">
        <head>Sūtras</head>
        <p>Sūtras are like paragraphs, but they are often formatted
  differently (without indentation, for example) and they do not have
  the “semantic baggage” of a prose paragraph. SARIT recommends the use
  of the <gi>ab</gi> element (“anonymous block”)
  with the attribute ~type="sutra"~.</p>
        <p>In the following example, the <gi>ab</gi>
  element includes, in addition to the text of the sutra, two typed
  labels that provide, respectively, the serial number of the adhikaraṇa
  in which the sutra occurs, and the position
  (<hi rendition="simple:bold">pūrvapakṣa</hi>,
  <hi rendition="simple:bold">uttarapakṣa</hi>, or
  <hi rendition="simple:bold">siddhānta</hi>) that the sutra
  represents.</p>
        <p>
          <hi rendition="simple:bold">Example 10</hi>
        </p>
        <p>
          <hi rendition="simple:italic">~/webstuff/eXist-stuff/sarit-pm/resources/img/sutra-img1-coloured.png</hi>
        </p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
	    <div>
    <ab type="sutra" n="2"><label type="adhikarana">2</label><label type="position">सि॰</label>
  एकस्यैवं पुनः श्रुतिरविशेषादनर्थकं हि स्यात् ॥ २
  </ab>
    <p> समिधो यजति, तनूनपातं यजति इत्येवमादिः पञ्चकृत्वोऽभ्यस्तो ...

  </p>
  </div>
</egXML>        <p/>
      </div>
      <div type="level1">
        <head>Dramatic elements</head>
        <p>SARIT uses the core elements of the TEI’s drama module for Sanskrit
  plays. Plays usually consist of divisions, such as an aṅka, in which
  various characters speak lines in prose or verse. The standard element
  for a “line” in this sense is <gi>sp</gi>: this
  contains the lines spoken by the character, either as prose
  (<gi>p</gi>) or verse
  (<gi>lg</gi>).</p>
        <p>The <gi>sp</gi> element may also contain a
  label for the speaker and stage directions. The speaker is encoded in
  the element <gi>speaker</gi>, and stage
  directions in the element <gi>stage</gi>. You
  should omit any formatting the editor has used to distinguish these
  elements.</p>
        <p>
          <hi rendition="simple:bold">Example 11</hi>
        </p>
        <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">~/webstuff/eXist-stuff/sarit-pm/resources/img/stage-img1-coloured.png</hi>
  alt=""</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
	
!!!<sp>
  !!!<speaker>राजा!!!</speaker>
  !!!<stage>स्वगतम!!!</stage>
  !!!<p>
किं नि खलु गीतमेवंविधमाकर्ण्येष्टजनविरहादृते ऽपि बलवदुत्कण्ठितो ऽस्मि । अथ वा ।
!!!</p>
  !!!<lg>
    !!!<l>रम्याणि वीक्ष्य मुधरांश्च निशम्य शब्दा!!!<caesura/>न्पर्युत्सुको भवति यत्सुखितो ऽपि जन्तुः ।!!!</l>
    !!!<l>तच्चेतसा स्मरति नूनमबोधपूर्वं!!!<caesura/> भावस्थिराणि जननान्तरसौहृदानि ॥ ९ ॥!!!</l>
  !!!</lg>
  !!!<stage>अस्मृतिनिमित्तमुन्मनस्कत्वं रूपयति!!!</stage>
!!!</sp>
</egXML>        <p/>
      </div>
      <div type="level1">
        <head>Labels and notes</head>
        <p>The source edition will sometimes have
  <hi rendition="simple:bold">labels</hi> added by the editor, which
  help to identify sections (below the level of the sections explicitly
  encoded as <gi>div</gi> elements), positions in
  an argument (<hi rendition="simple:bold">pūrvapakṣa</hi>,
  <hi rendition="simple:bold">uttarapakṣa</hi>,
  <hi rendition="simple:bold">siddhānta</hi>), or other features of the
  text. It will also sometimes have
  <hi rendition="simple:bold">notes</hi>, whether those are represented
  as footnotes, endnotes, or otherwise. It is possible to represent both
  labels and notes using TEI’s <gi>label</gi> and
  <gi>note</gi> elements.</p>
        <p>Because SARIT recommends encoding
  <hi rendition="simple:bold">structure</hi> rather than
  <hi rendition="simple:bold">presentation</hi>, it is important to have
  an encoding strategy for representing various types of notes and
  labels, and to document this strategy in the encoding declaration of
  the header. For example, your text might list variant readings and
  references in the footnotes, and hence you might encode these notes as
  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">!!!<note type="text-critical"/></egXML> or
  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">!!!<note type="reference"/></egXML>.
  Similarly, it is recommended to find consistent
  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">type</egXML> attributes for
  <gi>label</gi> elements as well, and to avoid
  the use of formatting-specific attributes (like
  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">place</egXML> and <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">rend</egXML>).</p>
        <p>In the example below the labels might be encoded as follows:</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
	
!!!<div>
  !!!<label type="position">2!!!</label>
  !!!<label type="position-person">भामहः!!!</label>
  !!!<lg>
    !!!<l>अगोनिवृत्तिः शब्दार्थो यदि गौः केन गम्यताम् ।!!!</l>
    !!!<l>गोशब्दं शृण्वतः पूर्वमगौः स्फुरतु चेतसि ॥ ५ ॥!!!</l>
  !!!</lg>
!!!</div>
</egXML>        <p>
          <hi rendition="simple:bold">Example 12</hi>
        </p>
        <p>
          <figure>
            <head>"label with @place and @type"</head>
            <graphic url="~/webstuff/sarit-webapp/exist-things/sarit-pm/resources/img/ex-label-tss.jpg"/>
            <figDesc>fig:</figDesc>
          </figure>
        </p>
        <p>Notes are often represented in printed editions with a
  <hi rendition="simple:bold">note marker</hi> in the main text, and the
  <hi rendition="simple:bold">note text</hi> either at the bottom of the
  page (as footnotes) or at the end of the chapter or text (as
  endnotes). <hi rendition="simple:bold">SARIT embeds notes into the
  text in their proper place.</hi> That is, wherever you see a note
  marker in the text, that is where you should place the
  <gi>note</gi> element.</p>
        <p>The content of the <gi>note</gi> element
  depends on the <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">type</egXML> of note that it represents.
  Typically, however, notes will contain a
  <gi>p</gi> element. For text-critical notes, the
  simple version of the guidelines recommends the use of prose
  paragraphs; more sophisticated methods are available in the full
  version of the guidelines.</p>
        <p>Attention must also be paid to the
  <hi rendition="simple:bold">language</hi> of the note, since in many
  cases it will differ from the language of the surrounding text. It is
  good practice to use the <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">xml:lang</egXML> attribute to
  identify the language of any element that differs from its parent
  element. This also includes sections of Sanskrit text quoted in notes,
  for which you may use the <gi>foreign</gi>
  element. For example:</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
	
!!!<p>यं नाट्यवेदं वेदेभ्यः सारमादाय ब्रह्मा कृतवान्, यत्संबद्धमभिनयं भरतश्चकार
करणाङ्गहारानकरोत्!!!<note xml:lang="en">!!!<p>A.T.A. !!!<foreign
xml:lang="sa-Latn">hārān anekān akarot!!!</foreign>.!!!</p>!!!</note> ... !!!</p>
</egXML>        <p>Note, finally, that editors will often insert references
  <hi rendition="simple:bold">into the text itself</hi>, and you are
  encouraged to use the <gi>note</gi> element for
  these additions, as in the following example. (See the full version of
  the guidelines for instructions regarding pointing references and
  canonical reference schemes.)</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
	
!!!<div>
  !!!<p>यथा तत्रैव (!!!<note type="reference">रत्ना॰ १।८!!!</note>—!!!</p>
  !!!<lg>
    !!!<l>‘प्रारम्भेऽस्मिन् स्वामिनो वृद्धिहेतौ दैवे चेत्थं दत्तहस्तावलभ्बे ।!!!</l>
    !!!<l>सिद्धेर्भ्रान्तिर्नास्ति सत्यं तथापि स्वेच्छाकारी भीत एवास्मि भर्तुः ॥’!!!</l>
  !!!</lg>
!!!</div>
</egXML>        <p/>
      </div>
      <div type="level1">
        <head>Quotations</head>
        <p>For the simple level of text encoding, we recommend encoding
  quotations “as-is.” That is, if the editor has used quotation marks or
  double quotation marks, put them into the digital text; if the editor
  has used bold-face text to represent quotations, use the
  <gi>hi</gi> tag (for “highlighted”). The reason
  for encoding quotations “as-is” is the possibility that identifying
  the beginning and end of quotations may require extensive checking by
  skilled readers, and the frequency with which quotations are
  represented inconsistently in printed editions. Of course, if project
  resources allow, quotations can be encoded by following the
  suggestions in the full version of the guidelines. </p>
        <div type="level2">
          <head>Where do I put इति?</head>
          <p>The particle इति, which marks quotations in Sanskrit, can be
    tricky: it often combines with the previous or following word, which
    can often mean that there is no typographic separation between a
    “verse” and the prose it’s embedded in. While there are ways of
    marking the beginning and ending of quotations, discussed more
    extensively in the SARIT Full guidelines, we don’t worry about
    quotations in SARIT Simple, and we are free to adopt the following
    straightforward principle: <hi rendition="simple:bold">follow the
    typography of the printed edition.</hi></p>
          <p>If the edition prints इति on the same line as the verse, include
    it there, within the <gi>l</gi> element; if it
    prints इति on a following line, then put it outside of the
    <gi>lg</gi> element.</p>
          <p>
            <hi rendition="simple:bold">Example 14: इति on the same
    line</hi>
          </p>
          <p>
            <figure>
              <head>"iti"</head>
              <graphic url="~/webstuff/sarit-webapp/exist-things/sarit-pm/resources/img/ex-iti-dp2.jpg"/>
              <figDesc>fig:</figDesc>
            </figure>
          </p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
	
!!!<lg>
  !!!<l>"वस्तूपलक्षणं यत्र सर्वाम् प्रसज्यते ।!!!</l>
  !!!<l>द्रव्यमित्युच्यते सोऽर्थो भेद्यत्वेन विवक्षितः ॥" इति ।!!!</l>
!!!</lg>
</egXML>          <p>
            <hi rendition="simple:bold">Example 15: इति merged with the last
    word in a verse</hi>
          </p>
          <p>
            <figure>
              <head>"iti same line" alt="iti same
      line"</head>
              <graphic url="~/webstuff/sarit-webapp/exist-things/sarit-pm/resources/img/ex-iti-vnt3.jpg"/>
              <figDesc>fig:</figDesc>
            </figure>
          </p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
	
!!!<lg>
  !!!<l>एकप्रत्यवमर्षस्य हेतुत्वाद्धीरभेदिनी!!!</l>
  !!!<l>एकधा हेतुभावेन व्यक्तीनामप्यभिन्नतेति ॥ (२५)!!!</l>
!!!</lg>
</egXML>          <p>
            <hi rendition="simple:bold">Example 16: इति on the following
    line</hi>
          </p>
          <p>
            <figure>
              <head>"iti on the next line"</head>
              <graphic url="~/webstuff/sarit-webapp/exist-things/sarit-pm/resources/img/ex-iti-pvsvt.jpg"/>
              <figDesc>fig:</figDesc>
            </figure>
          </p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
	
!!!<p>तदयुक्तं ।
!!!<lg>!!!<l>"तद्गतावेव शब्देभ्यो गम्यतेऽन्यनिवर्त्तनं ।!!!</l>!!!<l>न तत्र गम्यते कश्चिद्विशिष्टः केनचित्पर" ॥!!!</l>!!!</lg> (प्र. वा. १ । १२८)
इति ग्रन्थविरोधात् । नीरूपस्य चास्तित्वविरोधाच्छशविषाणवत् । नीरूपत्वा-
देव च न तस्याः प्रत्यक्षं ग्राहकं नाप्यनुमानं । सम्बन्धाभावात् ।!!!</p>
</egXML>
          <p/>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="level1">
        <head>Glossary</head>
        <list type="unordered">
          <item>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:bold">base text</hi>: The text on which
      the current text is a commentary.</p>
          </item>
        </list>
        <p>Since a <hi rendition="simple:bold">base text</hi> only makes sense
  in relation to a commentary on it, this term is only used within a
  commentary. Sections of the <hi rendition="simple:bold">base text</hi>
  that are quoted in the commentary (the current text) are enclosed in
  <gi>quote</gi> elements with the @type="base-text".</p>
        <list type="unordered">
          <item>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:bold">mūla</hi>: see
      <hi rendition="simple:bold">base text</hi>.</p>
          </item>
          <item>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:bold">root text</hi>: see
      <hi rendition="simple:bold">base text</hi>.</p>
          </item>
        </list>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
